<sect1><title>Affliction</title>
<para>
Affliction is the general term given to any condition which will affect a
character adversly, such as poison and disease. The mechanics for determining
the results of disease or poisoning are the same.
</para>

<sect2><title>Mechanics</title>
<para>
All poisons and diseases have a Virulence rating. In basic terms, the
virulence is a measure of the strength of the poison or disease; the
difficulty a person has in overcoming it's effects.
</para>

<para>
There are two stages of affliction: Partial Effects and Full Effects. The
effect on a creature will vary from affliction to affliction. Some example
afflictions will be given below.
</para>

<para>
A character will suffer partial effects from the affliction if they fail to
make their Afflicted roll, and likewise, they will suffer the full
effects if they fail to make their Resistance roll, as given below:
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Afflicted: d10-d10* + BOD + WIL &gt;= Virulence
</literal>
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Resistance: d10-d10* + BOD + FIT + 5 &gt;= Virulence
</literal>
</para>

<para>
Each affliction will also be given an Onset Time. It is after the Onset Time
has passed that a character is allowed to make their Afflicted roll.
</para>

<para>
Should a character succeed in making their Afflicted roll, they will suffer no
adverse effects from the affliction. Should the Afflicted roll be failed, and
after the Onset Time has passed again, the character is allowed to make their
Resistance roll. If the character makes their Resistance roll, the affliction
will proceed no further and the character will recover in (Virulence - WIL - FIT) days.
</para>

<para>
If the Resistance roll is failed, the character will suffer, in addition to
the partial effects, the full effects of the affliction, and, if they survive,
will recover in (Virulence - FIT) days.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Dosage</title>
<para>
Doseage for all afflictions is given as LD50 Doseage.
The LD50 doseage is defined as the dosage that will cause death in 50% of the
creatures exposed to that doseage.
The LD50 doseage is given or must be determined for each poison or disease.
</para>

<para>
For the administration of either larger or smaller doseages, the following
table is used to determine Virulence:
</para>

<table frame="all"><title>Virulence</title>
<tgroup cols="3" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colnum="3" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Dose</entry><entry>TD</entry><entry>Description</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>.125</entry><entry>10</entry></row>
<row><entry>.25</entry><entry>15</entry></row>
<row><entry>.5</entry><entry>20</entry><entry>(Half the LD50 Dose)</entry></row>
<row><entry>1.0</entry><entry>25</entry><entry>(LD50 dose)</entry></row>
<row><entry>2.0</entry><entry>30</entry><entry>(Double the LD50 Dose)</entry></row>
<row><entry>4.0</entry><entry>35</entry></row>
<row><entry>8.0</entry><entry>40</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<para>
For each doubling in administered dose, +5 is added to the TD. GM's should
note that, for poisons, an increased doseage administered will increase the
chance of the poison being detected.
</para>

<para>
Virulence Formula:
<literal>
Virulence TD = 25 + 5 * log(Multiple) / log(2)
</literal>
</para>

<para>
Multiple Formula:
<literal>
Multiple (= Dose / LD50) = 2^((TD-25) / 5)
</literal>
</para>

<para>
All LD50 doseages are given assuming roughly human body size and weight.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Sample Afflictions</title>
<sect3><title>Poisons</title>
<para>
Sodium Cyanide

<screen>
LD50: 1.1 g
Onset Time: 5 minutes
Partial Effects: -3 to STR, -3 to FIT, 2d6 pts of injury
Full Effects: -2 STR, -2 FIT, 3d6 pts of injury
Comments: has a distinctive burnt almond taste. When put in acid, generates
hydrogen cyanide gas.
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Tetrodotoxin

<screen>
LD50: .001 g
Onset Time: 2 minutes
Partial effects: -3 DEX, -1 AGI
Full effects: -2 DEX, -1 AGI, 3d6 pts of injury
Comments: Found in puffer-fish, and with a low LD50 would be good for coating
weapons, but also effective as ingested poison. Neurotoxin.
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Sarin

<screen>
LD50: .001 g
Onset Time: 2 minutes
Partial effects: -1 DEX
Full Effects: -2 DEX, 5d6 pts of injury
Comments: Nerve gas. Effective as contact poison, inhaled, or ingested. 
Neurotoxin.
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Bungarotoxin

<screen>
LD50: .012 g
Onset time: 10 minutes
Partial effects: -2 STR, -2 FIT
Full effects: -1 FIT, 3d6 pts injury
Comments: Common neurotoxin from snakes.
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Amanitin

<screen>
LD50: .01 g
Onset time: 30 minutes
Partial effects: -2 STR, -2 FIT
Full effects: -1 STR, 3d6 pts injury
Comments: Poison found in some poisonous mushrooms. If whole mushrooms or
pieces are eaten, then the LD50 dose becomes 10 g. Concentrated form effective
ingested and injected.
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Imp's Sting

<screen>
LD50: One sting
Onset time: 10 seconds
Partial effects: Comatosed in 10 days.
Full effects: Death within 1 minute.
Comments: This is the main reason imps are so feared.
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Diseases</title>
<para>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
