<sect1><title>Experience Awards</title>
<para>
Experience Points (EP) are awarded in five categories
</para>

<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
<listitem><para>Adventure/goals fulfilled</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Bard's tale/heroics</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Conflict/danger</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Forethought/ingenuity</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Growth/interaction</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
1-6 dice can be awarded in each category depending on the significance of 
the event or session.
</para>
 
<table frame="all"><title>Experience Dice Award</title>
<tgroup cols="3" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Significance</entry><entry>Dice (d6)</entry><entry>Constant</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>None</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>0</entry></row>
<row><entry>Noteworthy</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>4</entry></row>
<row><entry>Impressive</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>8</entry></row>
<row><entry>Spectacular</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>16</entry></row>
<row><entry>Legendary</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>24</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
 
<example><title>Simple examples by category</title>
<screen>
(a1) surviving one session whilst actively adventuring (i.e., in the 
     midst of potential danger and/or intrigue)

(a4) successfully completing a campaign requiring a significant expenditure
     of time and resources in an environment of considerable danger

(a6) as above but one of those "save the world" type conclusions

(b2) a character rescues a hostage from bandits

(b4) loot in hand, a character leaps off a balcony, grabs the swinging
     chandelier, completes a somersault through a stained glass window,
     and lands safely on the snow covered ground outside

(c0) Ronan defeats an orc

(c1) a character wins a Dragonshah tournament

(c2) a character defeats an opponent but is seriously wounded

(c4) a character leads an army and scores a crushing victory

(c6) David beats Goliath

(d1) a character takes a simple precaution that saves the party's bacon 
     (they spiked the door)

(d2) a character exhibits a novel use of an attribute or skill

(d4) by logic, deduction, and a touch of intuition, a character uncovers 
     a major plot element that leads to the successful conclusion of an 
     adventure

(e1) a character attends a social engagement and makes a good impression 
     on the assembled nobility

(e2) a character displays convictions of belief in the face of ridicule

(e4) a character saves the life of a servitor

(e4) using only accrued clout and connections, a character successfully
     initiates a socio-political "power-play" from a distance

(e6) a character with a barbarian background becomes king of a mighty
     nation through repute, force of arms, and power politics
</screen>
</example>
  
<sect2><title>Using experience dice</title>
<para>
Once the experience dice have been awarded by the Game Master, the player
has three options:
</para>

<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>
He can roll the dice and get a number of experience points equal to their total.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
He can play safe and get a number of experience points equal to 4 times the
number of experience dice (1 dice = 4 EP).
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
He can divide his experience dice between the two options above,
choosing to roll some of them and to cash in the remaining ones.
The player must decide how many dice will be rolled before he starts rolling.
</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
Of course, the Game Master may rule that some options are not available if he
feels that they are detrimental to the game.
</para>

<example><title>Using Experience Dice</title>
<screen>
Say a player is awarded 10 experience dice. The player could:

1) Roll all 10 dice, which would generate from 10 to 60 points,
   with an average of 35.
2) Exchange the 10 dice for 40 experience points.
3) Roll 3 dice and cash in the remaining 7, which would generate
   between 31 and 46, with an average of 38.5.
</screen>
</example>

<sect3><title><emphasis>Experience Dice During Play (Optional)</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
During a game session, if a character has some experience dice saved up,
he may use them for purposes other than skill advancement.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
In this case, Experience Dice can be used for:
</emphasis>
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Improving a Task Resolution (d10-d10*) roll</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Increasing an Impact roll</emphasis></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
<emphasis>
To avoid a penalty, a player must declare the use of experience dice BEFORE he
makes his roll. He should tell the GM that he wishes to modify his pending dice
roll with some experience dice. After the GM has been told how many experience
dice are going to be used in this way, the player rolls the total of the
original dice plus how ever many experience dice he told the GM he was going to
use.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
If a player wishes to modify a die roll AFTER he has rolled the dice, he
must do so at a penalty of three times the cost; therefore, the player pays
three experience dice for each die added to the roll.
</emphasis>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
