<sect1><title>Character Concept</title>
<para>
The character concept is a general idea of what you want your character to be
like, something that you find interesting.
Try to envision your character's personality, species, background, gender, and
even appearance.
</para>

<para>
During the character creation you can always change and alter this concept to
suit your ideas, but at least it gives you a starting point.
</para>

<para>
By answering the following six basic questions you can create a solid,
believable character: Who, What, When, Where, Why and How.
</para>

<formalpara><title>Who?</title>
<para>
This question helps define the character's personality by identifying
the people around him. Defining who the character is inculdes determening
aspects such as:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Who were the character's parents?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Who were the character's childhood friends?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Who are the character's friends/enemies?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Who are the character's most common foes?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Who does the character talk to when he's upset?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Who does the character love/hate?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Who does the character trust?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Who does the character work for (if any)?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Who started the character on the road to be an adventurer?</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

This question not only helps define the character, but also other NPCs in the
campaign world.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>What?</title>
<para>
This question answers more about the character's life, history and current
status.

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>What did the character do for a living before he became an adventurer?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>What prompted the character to become an adventurer?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>What color is the character's hair/eyes?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>What is the character's age?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>What does the character do in his free time - when he's not on the road as an adventurer?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>What does the character do when he's alone?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>What are the character's favorite foods, music, books?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>What is the character's personality like?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>What are the character's ethnic, educational and social backgrounds?</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>When?</title>
<para>
Answering this question sets the time frame for the character and for many of
the other questions.

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>When was the character born?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>When did the character decide to become an adventurer?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>When did the character arrive where he is now (city/planet/plane of existence)?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>When does the character get up in the morning/go to bed?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>When does the character practice his Skills?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>When does the character visit his family/friends?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>When did the character meet the other characters?</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Where?</title>
<para>
Answers to this question gives the locations for the events in the characters
life. They provide a home and anchor for the character.

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Where was the character born/raised?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Where does the character live when he's not on the road adventuring?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Where does the character practice his Skills?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Where did the character learn his Skills?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Where did the character go on his last vacation?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Where is the character's favorite resturant?</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Why?</title>
<para>
These are probably the most important questions. These questions define the
character's motivation and commitment to do what he sees as right.

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Why did the character first decide to become an adventurer?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Why is the character where he is now?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Why does the character work with the other characters?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Why does the character use the weapon he does?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Why did the character choose to learn and improve the Skills he has?</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>How?</title>
<para>
These questions round out many of the earlier questions.

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>How did the character gain his weapons and his fighting Skills?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>How does the character use his abilities (silly stunts, combat tactics, etc.)?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>How does the character pass the time between adventures?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>How does the character get around every day (by foot, horse, special abilities)?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>How does the character maintain a "normal" life and still find time to be an adventurer?</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</formalpara>

<para>
These questions are just samples. You can go into as much depth as you like.
When you are satisfied it's time to move on to the next step in the character
creation prosess.
</para>
</sect1>
