<sect1><title>Gifts and Foibles</title>
<para>
Gifts and Foibles cover anything not covered by Talents.
They have EP Costs, and may be bought with EPs when the character is created.
</para>

<para>
These are intended to cover special or unusual situations, like
"fire resistance" or "shape change." If the genre permits, psychological Gifts
or Foibles may also be permitted, such as "fear of snakes" or "high pain
threshold". EP Costs are assigned by the GM or genre.
</para>

<para>
Gifts and Foibles may be set out by the GM in advance, or made up on
the spot to allow good character conceptions.
</para>

<para>
Gift or Foible EP Costs will depend on how they actually affect
game play for the character. A guideline for assigning EP Costs is given below.
</para>

<para>
Note that this scheme is a guideline only. If the result is unsatisfactory,
the GM should alter it until it "feels" right. This scheme should just outline
the general range of EP Cost values.
</para>

<para>
The base cost is 5 EP for an Gift, or -5 for a Foible. This value
is then multiplied by 1 to 4, depending on whether the Gift or Foible
is slight, moderate, significant or extreme:
</para>

<screen>
Gift/Foible is:                  Severity Multiplier
Normal:                          x 0
Mild/slight:                     x 1
Moderate:                        x 2
Rare/severe/significant:         x 3
Crippling/exceptional/extreme:   x 4
</screen>

<para>
The value is also multiplied by a factor of 1/2 to 3, depending on whether the
Gift or Foible comes into play rarely, occasionally, often or all the time:
</para>

<screen>
Gift/Foible:                    Frequency Multiplier
Rarely comes into play:         x 1/2
Occasionally comes into play:   x 1
Often comes into play:          x 2
Always comes into play:         x 3
</screen>

<para>
Note that a single quality may involve a number of separate Gifts or
Foibles. Rather than trying to figure out a general sense of how
giftous the package is as a whole, each major aspect of the quality should
be defined and assigned EP Costs separately.
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
For example, a "vampire" might include:

Dies in contact with direct sunlight (always an extreme foible): -60
Dependent upon human blood (occasionally a significant foible): -15
Repelled by crosses and garlic (often a significant foible):  -30
Can shape-change into a bat (often an extreme gift):  40
...and so on.
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
It might seem obvious, but it is nonetheless important to state that any
Gift or Foible must be evaluated according to its effect in the
particular campaign. Having a fear of heights is worth no EP at all if the
entire campaign is to be conducted underground.
</para>

<para>
NOTE: All Gifts and Foibles that cause mental or physical alterations,
can be activated once per round, gives the character 1 Fatigue when activated,
and imobilizes the character for one round after the activation is done
(unless otherwise noted).
This is due to the extreme mental and physical strain.
</para>

<sect2><title>Sample Gifts</title>
<screen>
Beauty +5 * Severity
  Beauty simply defines how good a character looks in terms of sheer 
  physical attractiveness, when regarded by one of his/her own Species. 
  It can be particularly important when you have no time to argue or 
  express yourself but must still leave a good impression. Gives a +1 
  bonus to Seduction and similar Skills per point of Effectiveness.

Ambidexterity +20

?Animal Empathy              +20

Regeneration (even limbs grow back)
   1 injury/rd   +200
   1 injury/min  +150
   1 injury/hour +100

   +100 if the regeneration brings the character back form death.

--- To be removed --------------------------------
-Healing/Regeneration        Variable
   Per INJURY point             +5 * Recovery Rate
      Recovery Rate
         per 5 hours            x2
         per hour              x10
         per minute           x600
	 per round           x6000
         per second         x36000
   Can replace limbs         +1000

(EP Cost = INJURY healed * 5 * Recovery Rate)
--------------------------------------------------

Nightvision (5 * 3 * 2) +30
   Unless there is complete darkness, the character can see as
   if it was midday on a cloudy day, but in shades of gray.

Infravision (5 * 2 * 2) +20
   Enables the character to "see" the heat emitted form the environment
   and other creatures.

Shape Change (5 * 4 * 2) +40
   The character can shift into one other shape.
   May be picked several times.

Innate Skill Bonus, ISB      ISB * (ISB + 1) * Skill's Base Cost / 2
   Ex: Climbing, ISB +3 = 3 * 4 * 3 / 2 = +18

Sense Aura (5 * 3 * 3) +45
   Characters with this gift are able to sense the "nature" of other beings.
   Upper planars will usually have bright/light auras and lower planars
   will usually have dark auras. The color and brightness reflects the
   creature's personality and motivation.

Invisibility (5 * 4 * 2) +40
   Turns the character and a thin layer of clothing invisible for as long as
   the character is mentaly aware. If the character falls unconscious or
   asleep the effect fades.

Immunities
   elements (fire, cold, electricity, ...) +50 per element
   non-magical weapons +100

Magic Resistance +5 per +1 to resistance
   The bonus is added to all resistance rolls vs. magical attacks.

Flying (5 * 3 * 2) +30 (+10 per additional 5 m/rd)
   Enables the character to fly 5 m/rd. Normal encumbrance penalties apply.
   Ex: Flying 20 m/rd = +60 (+30 + 10 * 3)

Teleport +50 (+10 per additional 10 meters)
   A character with this ability can teleport 10 meters in any direction.
   The target area does not have to be seen, but it would sertenly make it
   safer. (GM's descretion).

Planeshift +100
   This can be quite dangerous. Before activating the ability, the character
   must be familiar with the target location to ensure safety. He must be
   able to somehow see or focus on the target location.

Telepathy
   One other person          +50   (+10 ?)
   All within same species  +500  (+100 ?)
   All species             +5000 (+1000 ?)

   Must be within line of sight; that is, you must be able to somehow see
   the person you're trying to communiate with.

Don't need sleep (find a better name) (+5 * 3 * 2) +30

Immortal +50
   An importal character does not face the problem of dying from old age.
   He can still be die form injury, though.
</screen>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Sample Foibles</title>
<screen>
Ugliness                 -5 * Severity
   Reverse of Beauty gift. Gives a -1 penalty to Seduction and similar skills 
   per point of Severity.

Abnormal voice           -5 * Severity
   Character stutters, squeaks, rumbles, etc. enough that people have a hard
   time understanding him/her. Skills that require a voice are reduced by
   -Severity.

Color blindness          -5 * Severity
   1: Character is green/red color blind and suffers a -1 penalty to any
      skill check requiring the use of color.
   2: -2 to any skill check requiring the use of color.
   3: -3 to any skill check requiring the use of color.
   4: Character is unable to see much difference in colors at all. People
      who are able to see through the character's eyes will see that
      everything is a grainy black-n-white. -4 penalty

Deafness                 -10 * Severity
   1: Character is deaf in one ear or sometimes unable to hear things being
      said. GM should require a PER check when the character is in a noisy
      or audibly distracting situation.
   2: Character is often unable to hear things. GM should require a PER
      check whenever the character is being spoken to in a normal voice.
      Character can hear if being shouted at. Skills requiring hearing are
      at -2.
   3: Character must be shouted at in order for him/her to have a chance to
      hear what is being said. GM should require a PER check (-5 if not
      being shouted at)  Skills requiring hearing are at -4.
   4: Character is completely deaf.

Eyesight, poor           -15 * Severity
   1: Glasses/spectacles needed or PER is decreased by 2.
   2: Glasses/spectacles needed or PER is decreased by 4.
   3: Glasses/spectacles needed or PER is decreased by 6.
   4: Character is blind.

Eyesight, missing eye    -15
   Character is only able to see through one eye, and thus lacks stereo
   vision.
   PER is lowered by -5 for anything occurring on blind side.

Distinguishing mark       -5
   Character has something distinguishing or odd about his appearance. (an
   eyeball not in line with the other, an abnormally large nose, a scar, etc.)
   People will easily remember the character based on the mark. Skills using
   BEA are decreased by -1.

Mutated skin             -10 * Severity
   1: Acne, small rashes. BEA skills decreased by -1.
   2: Albino, skin discolorations. BEA skills decreased by -2.
   3: Skin blotches, rashes covering most of body. BEA skills decreased by -3.
   4: Extreme skin blotches. BEA skills at -4. Sunlight causes damage.

Overweight               -20 * Severity
   1: -1 FIT
   2: -1 FIT, -1 AGI
   3: -2 FIT, -1 AGI
   4: -2 FIT, -2 AGI

Phobias                   -5 * Severity
   agoraphobia     (crowds, public places, open areas)
   arachnophobia   (spiders)
   claustrophobia  (enclosed/narrow places)
   xenophobia      (foreigners, strangers, strange/foreign things)

Primarily handed          -5 * Severity
   Character is dependent on one hand more so than normal. Using other hand
   results in a penalty of -Severity.

Sterile                   -5
   Character is unable to produce children. Character may suffer social
   consequences as a result.

Enemy (5 * Severity * Frequency)
   Severity
      1: Less powerfull than you
      2: As powerfull as you
      3: More powerfull than you
      4: Way out of your league
</screen>
</sect2>
</sect1>
