<sect1><title>Fatigue and Casting Time</title>
<para>
Casting spells is neither instantaneous, nor easy. While some very simple
spells can be cast in one or two seconds and with little effort, most spells
take at least a full round to cast and leave the magic user fatigued.
</para>

<para>
When casting a spell, the magic user has to channel the magical energy,
which is a very demanding activity for the magus body. The fatigue created
by the spell is thus proportional to the amount of energy tapped, i.e. to
the Source Task Difficulty. The Fatigue heap of the magus is increased by
one plus one fifth of the Source TD, rounding up, after the spell has been
completed. If the spell fails, the magus suffers from only half the normal
Fatigue associated with the spell. This Fatigue affects all subsequent
actions, including other spells cast by the magus.
</para>

<para>
While tapping a Source of magical energy takes time, it is a fast process
which does not impact much on the casting time of the spell. Harnessing and
shaping that energy into a useful spells takes more time and the casting
time of a spell therefore depends on the Conductor TD. The casting time of a
spell is equal to 5 plus the Conductor TD in seconds. The spell goes off in
the round during which its casting ends.
</para>

<example><title>Fatigue And Casting Time For Fireball Spell</title>
<screen>
The "Fireball" spell has a Conductor TD of 5 and thus takes 10
seconds to cast, going off in the round after the casting has begun. A spell
with a casting time of 18 seconds would go off in the third round of the
casting.
</screen>
</example>

<para>
In the DNET system, each round lasts 6 seconds, so that there are 10
rounds per minute.
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
OPTIONAL:
If Fatigue is not used with the rest of the rules, the game master may wish to
simplify its application for the magi. One option is to increment Fatigue
normally when casting a spell, but not to apply it as a penalty to subsequent
actions. As a limiting factor to spell casting, the magi are only able to cast
spells for which their Source skill is greater than their Fatigue heap.
</emphasis>
</para>

<example><title><emphasis>Alternate Fatigue</emphasis></title>
<screen>
<emphasis>
If a magician has a skill of 15 in the "Elemental Power of Energy",
he could only cast the Fireball spell has long as his Fatigue heap
remains below 15.
</emphasis>
</screen>
</example>
</sect1>
