<sect1><title>General Principles of Magic</title>
<table frame="all"><title>Magician Skill Competency</title>
<tgroup cols="3" align="center">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Skill</entry><entry>Competency</entry><entry>Description</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>1 - 5</entry><entry>Apprentice</entry><entry>Minor self-control, sense the most obvious, immediate vicinity, line of sight, basic knowledge, general impressions, detect resonance.</entry></row>
<row><entry>6 - 10</entry><entry>Journeyman</entry><entry>Moderate self-control, minor control outisde self, minor manipulation of appearances, affect simple life patterns (plants and microscopic lifeforms), control/manipulate simple/single events, re-direction, equilibrium is maintained.</entry></row>
<row><entry>11 - 15</entry><entry>Craftsman</entry><entry>Major self-control, moderate control outside self, moderate manipulation of appearances, minor fundamental manipulation/transformation, minor creation (plants and microscopic lifeforms), affect moderate life patterns (insects).</entry></row>
<row><entry>16 - 20</entry><entry>Adept</entry><entry>Extreme self-control, major control outside self, major manipulation of appearances, moderate fundamental manipulation/transformation, moderate creation (insects), affect complex life patterns (mammals and reptiles).</entry></row>
<row><entry>21 - 25</entry><entry>Master</entry><entry>Extreme control outside self, major fundamental manipulation/transformation, major creation (mammals and reptiles), affect any life pattern.</entry></row>
<row><entry>26+</entry><entry>Grandmaster</entry><entry>Pretty much no limit.</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<example><title>Magical Effect TDs</title>
<screen>
TD = 5:
Find true north, heal bruises and stop minor bleeding on yourself, slightly
heighten your senses, change hair/eye color, add/remove a few years of
wrinkels on self, determen someones actual age, sense general emotions
of one person or area.

TD = 10:
Heal open fleshwounds and minor bone fractures on yourself, alter weight,
height or length of arms or legs with app. 10%, heal or destroy simple life
patterns, co-locate perception, read surface thoughts, slow effects of poisons/
deases, mentaly give simple impulses to others (love/hate/rage/friendliness).

TD = 15:
Regenerate lost limbs, heal broken bones and severed muscels on yourself,
alter self with app. 50%, add a finger/toe, create a rose, destroy a
bee hive, co-locate self, read subcounscious thoughts, calm/arouse emotions,
mental communication, cheat death for a few years, take appearance of a cat,
neutralize poisons/deseases.

TD = 20:
Heal any wound on yourself, add/remove an arm/leg permanently,
co-locate others, control conscious thoughts/emotions, cheat death
for a few decades, transform yourself into cat.

TD = 25:
Create a dog or a humanoid or a clone of yourself, cheat death for a
few centuries, transform your mother into a cow :), heal any wound
(except death) on anyone, control subconscios thought/emotion,
reprogram personality.
</screen>
</example>

<para>
The listed examples does not apply to every magical focus. See the description
of the foci to determen what each one can do.
</para>

<sect2><title>Paradigms and Magic</title>
<para>
Think of reality as a medium that has strong preferences for a specific
paradigm, in any given place. Different places (can) have different paradigms.
In any given place, then, there is one paradigm. That paradigm has a lot to do
with what the residents believe now (and/or have believed in the past).
It is important to understand, however, that while any paradigm is just a way
of doing reality, each paradigm is richly self-consistant, and that a local
area's paradigm changes much more slowly than the beliefs of any individual
resident. The momentary beliefs or confusions of residents is not the sum of
local reality.
</para>

<para>
Each paradigm is a system of explanations and methods for doing things.
Two systems are involved with every instance of magic.
</para>

<para>
1: The local static reality.
</para>

<para>
2: The magician's paradigm.
</para>

<para>
When you think about an act of magic, consider: did the two systems agree
(mostly) about the method/concept behind how the act was done?
The second thing to consider is, did anyone recognize that the two systems did
not agree (if they didn't)?
</para>

<para>
All the magic a magician does must have an explanation native to his own
paradigm. Magicans never do "raw magic," but they do know how to explain
everything they know how to do.
</para>

<para>
Next, it's important to understand that local realities are independant and
self-consistant.
</para>

<sect3><title>Vulgar vs Nonvulgar</title>
<para>
Something is nonvulgar when the method used to produce a reality-impacting
event is "believeable" by the standards of the local paradigm. Otherwise, it is
vulgar. Vulgarity does not hinge on what people in fact see. Vulgarity does not
hinge on any "trick" or bogus explanation for a magical effect, only on the
real explanations used by the local paradigm and the magician's paradigm.
People cannot sway the vulgarity of an isolated act of magic. They can either
witness it, or not. Vulgarity is solely an issue of whether the magician chooses
to use methods from within his paradigm that conform (adequately) to the local
paradigm, and is not an issue involving the perceptions of specific people.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Witnessed vs Not Witnessed</title>
<para>
"Witnessed" happens only when people recognize that a specific event and method
violates the static reality. If they don't see it at all, it's "without
witnesses." If they believe in the way they think it was done, but that way is
not the way it was really done, it's "without witnesses."
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>How Paradigms Affect Spell Success</title>
<para>
If the effect is nonvulgar: subtract 5 from TD.
</para>

<para>
If the effect is vulgar, but without witnesses: add 5 to TD.
</para>

<para>
If the effect is vulgar, and with witnesses: add 10 to TD.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>The Laws of Magic</title>
<para>
We are now ready to go into a description of the basic ways in which magical
phenomena seem to behave. The Laws of Magic are not legislative laws but,
like those of physics or of musical harmony, are practical observations that
have been accumulating over the course of thousands of years, with remarkable
similarity in almost every known human culture.

Those of you who prefer to remain skeptical as to the reality of psychic
phenomena and the systems of magic developed to control them will at least find
these Laws an interesting and detailed guide to what psychologists and
anthropologists so patronizingly refer to as "magical thinking."
</para>

<para>
Those of you who play magicians as characters will find these Laws a remarkably
concise guide to the ways in which most magicians, at least on this world,
believe magic to work. Most of the technical motivations of magic-using
characters, before, during and after using magic, will be based on these laws.
</para>

<para>
Along with each Law listed, I'll include key words to help in memorization.
These phrases are gross generalizations, but have the advantage of being brief
and easy to remember.
</para>

<para>
It's entirely possible that there are other Laws of Magic, however, I'm
currently unaware of any that are held to by most magicians on this planet.
Individual game designers and referees are free to invent new ones for their
game universes, but they will probably give the most accurate magic simulations
if they are congruent to these ones listed.
</para>

<sect3><title>The Law of Knowledge</title>
<para>
Essence: Understanding brings control; the more that is known about a subject,
the easier it is to exercise control over it.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: This Law is so fundamental that hardly any work on magic has ever
been published without mentioning it. The comments in Chivalry &amp; Sorcery
are quite appropriate here: "The Magick User might be compared to a combination
philosopher-sage-research scientist only those activities which directly aim at
increasing one's mastery of Magic itself can give the magician any experience
worthwhile to him." These comments are most accurate for intellectual magicians
of the theurgical sort but are more or less true of most other magic users as
well.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Knowledge is power.
</para>
</sect3>
 
<sect3><title>The Law of Self-Knowledge</title>
<para>
Essence: The most important kind of magical knowledge is about oneself;
familiarity with one's own strengths and weaknesses is vital to success
as a magician.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Most magicians quickly discover their own flairs and flaws. After all,
this is a large part of what Apprenticeship is all about. This is also why
"Evil Magicians" are comparatively rare in the real world (especially in the
"higher ranks") because a dedication to "Evil for Evil's sake" is almost always
due to a lack of introspection and self-awareness.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Know thyself.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Cause &amp; Effect</title>
<para>
Essence: If exactly the same actions are done under exactly the same conditions,
they will usually be associated with exactly the same "results";
similar strings of events produce similar outcomes.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Magicians have at least as much belief in cause and effect as modern
physicists do, they just know that a good ritual, like a good poem or a good
bread recipe, isn't always absolutely predictable.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Control every variable and you control every change, lotsa luck!
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Synchronicity</title>
<para>
Essence: Two or more events happening at the same time are likely to have
more associations in common than the merely temporal; very few events ever
really happen in isolation from nearby events.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: If you manage to pin a professional debunker against a wall (be
careful, they get nasty when cornered) you'll find that the word "coincidence"
is a scientistic term of exorcism, used to banish the demons of non-material,
and therefore unscientific, causality.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Coincidence is seldom mere.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Association</title>
<para>
Essence: If any two or more patterns have elements in common, the patterns
interact through those common elements, and control of one pattern facilitates
control over the other(s), depending (among other factors) upon the number,
type and duration of common elements involved.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: This is probably one of the most important of the magical Laws and
is directly connected to most of the others.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Commonality controls.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Similarity</title>
<para>
Essence: Effects are liable to have an outward physical or mental appearance
similar to their causes.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Having an accurate image/sound/smell of an object or being facilitates
control over it or them.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Look-alikes are alike.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Contagion</title>
<para>
Essence: Objects or beings in physical or psychic contact with each other
continue to interact after separation.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Everyone your character has ever touched has a psychic link with him,
though it is (probably) pretty weak unless the contact was intense and/or
repeated frequently. Naturally having a part of someone's body (nails, hair,
spit, blood, etc.) gives the best contagion link. Almost as good are objects of
clothing, handkerchiefs, bedsheets, etc., that have absorbed sweat or other
bodily fluids from the being your character wishes to magically influence.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Magic is contagious.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Positive Attraction</title>
<para>
Essence: Like attracts like; to create a particular reality you must put out
energy of a similar sort.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: This Law is often used in attraction spells, by saturating the aura
of the magician or client with symbols and energies similar to those wanted.
It's also commonly cited for moralistic purposes to discourage unwanted
magical behavior, on the grounds that behaving badly will attract evil or bad
luck. This Law may refer to morphic resonances; the tendency for energy shapes
to complete themselves, or perhaps wave entrainment, which is the ability of
particular vibrations to set up matching vibrations in nearby energy patterns.
If either of these phenomena happen with psychic energy fields, they could
easily cause the effects usually referred to by this Law.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: That which is sent, returns.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Negative Attraction</title>
<para>
Essence: Like attracts unlike; energy and actions often attract their opposites.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: People say that like attracts like, but they also say that opposites
attract. This paradox can be reconciled by contemplating the classic yin-yang
symbol. The two halves of the yin-yang are opposite in color, but they are
identical in shape; thus opposite and similar on two different levels of
reality (or universes of discourse). Yet the two halves both attract and repel
each other in an eternal circular dance (see the Law of Polarity below).
</para>

<para>
Any phenomenon more complex than a bacteria can be viewed on several levels,
so you can usually find ways in which any two phenomena can be seen as either
opposite or similar, depending on which of these Laws of Attraction you are
interested in emphasizing.
</para>

<para>
The reason this hasn't been clear before is that Western Dualism usually picks
one aspect of existence that two phenomena have and insist that it is the only
important aspect as far as judging the phenomena to be similar or opposite.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Opposites attract.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Names</title>
<para>
Essence: Knowing the complete and true name of an object, being or process
gives one complete control over it.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: This works because a name is a definition (yes, even Harold, Marie,
Xunte, and Jasmine were at one time) as well as a contagion link. Perhaps more
importantly, it works because knowing the complete and true name of something
or someone means that you have achieved a complete understanding of its or his
nature. This is why, in most pre-industrial cultures, people are given secret
names as well as public names, and why the sharing of a secret name is such an
act of trust because the secret name is considered to be very close to, if not
identical with, the person's true name.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: What's in a name? Everything!
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Words of Power</title>
<para>
Essence: There exist certain words that are able to alter the internal and
external realities of those uttering them, and their power may rest in the very
sounds of the words as much as in their meanings.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Many words are names and most have known definitions. Barbarous words
of power are (currently, if not originally) nonsense words that nonetheless can
release certain psychic phenomena and states. Very many magical tools require
words to be in-scribed upon them and/or to be said over them during their
creation.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: A word to the wise is sufficient.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Personification</title>
<para>
Essence: Any phenomenon may be considered to be alive and to have a
personality, that is, to be an entity or being, and may be effectively dealt
with thusly.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: This Law is based on fundamental human thought processes and does
make doing magic, especially with abstract concepts, much easier. Most
magicians who do weather magic, for example, personify the winds and the
clouds, and thus find focusing their APK (atomic psychokinesis, psychokinesis
done upon the molecular, atomic or subatomic levels) upon the atmosphere much
easier.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Anything can be a person.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Invocation</title>
<para>
Essence: It is possible to establish internal communication with entities
from either inside or outside of oneself, said entities seeming to be inside of
oneself during the communication process.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Either Invocation or Evocation can control the spirit communication
processes known as inspiration, conversation, channeling (mediumship), and
temporary possession.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Beings within...
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Evocation</title>
<para>
Essence: It is possible to establish external communication with entities from
either inside or outside of oneself, said entities seeming to be outside of
oneself during the communication process.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Evocation is the Law that controls most summonings.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: ... Beings without.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Identification</title>
<para>
Essence: It is possible through maximum association between the elements of
oneself and those of another being to actually become that being to the point
of sharing its knowledge and weilding its power.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: This is the Law that controls most lengthy or permanent possession
phenomena.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: You can become another.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Infinite Data</title>
<para>
Essence: The number of phenomena to be known is infinite; one will never run
out of things to learn.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: The best possible example of this is the Internet. You could spend
24 hours per day, seven days per week, and still never see 1% of the
information that's out there and most of human knowledge isn't on the Net yet
(as of 1998, anyway).
</para>

<para>
Keywords: There's always something new.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Finite Senses</title>
<para>
Essence: Every sense mechanism of every entity is limited by both range and
type of data perceived.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Many real phenomena exist which may be outside the sensory scanning
ability of any given entity.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Nobody can see everything. Just because it's invisible doesn't mean
it's not there.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Personal Universes</title>
<para>
Essence: Every sentient being lives in and quite possibly creates a unique
universe which can never be 100% identical to that lived in by another.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: So-called reality is in fact a matter of consensus opinions. There is
no single Reality that exists (whether people like it or not that odd idea is
popular due to monotheistic theologies and the Scientism they spawned) instead
there are multiple and frequently contradictory realities all existing
simultaneously. This Law may or may not be the same as the Law of Infinite
Universes.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: You live in your cosmos and I'll live in mine.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Infinite Universes</title>
<para>
Essence: The total number of universes into which all possible combinations
of existing phenomena could be organized is infinite.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Some people consider this Law to refer to the alternate probability
worlds of science fiction, however, it has a much wider application.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: All things are possible, though some are more probable than others.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Pragmatism</title>
<para>
Essence: If a pattern of belief or behavior enables a being to survive and to
accomplish chosen goals, than that belief or behavior is "true" or "real" or
"sensible" on whatever levels of reality are involved.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: If it works, it's true.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of true Falsehoods</title>
<para>
Essence: It's possible for a concept or act to violate the truth patterns of a
given universe (including an individual's or group's part of a consensus
reality) and yet to still be "true", provided that it works in a specific
context.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: A data pattern may be true on one level of reality and false on
another, depending upon the circumstances involved.
</para>

<para>
For example, on the normal scholarly level of reality the Thunder Gods are
parts of the quaint mythologies of our ignorant ancestors and therefore false,
but on the level of reality involved in magical Rain-Making they are very real
indeed.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: If it's a paradox it's probably true.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Synthesis</title>
<para>
Essence: The synthesis of two or more opposing patterns of data will produce a
new pattern that will be truer than either of the first ones were, that is, it
will be applicable to more realities (or levels of reality).
</para>

<para>
Remarks: This new pattern will not necessarily be a compromise but may be
something new.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Synthesis reconciles.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Polarity</title>
<para>
Essence: Any pattern of data can be split into (at least) two patterns with
opposing characteristics, and each will contain the essence of the other
within itself.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Polarity should not be confused with dualism, a mistake that
Westerners have been making for four thousand years and which has quite
possibly led to more all-around misery than any other theological concept in
history. Dualism assumes that opposites are at war with one another; polarity
assumes that they embrace. The creators of D&amp;D did the game world a major
favor when they made neutrality a part of the political and moral alignments in
their game. The "Law vs. Chaos" and "Good vs. Evil" alignment systems so common
in fantasy games are dangerous oversimplifications but the addition of
neutrality and amorality (not to mention the new alignments that have been
invented by players and referees, such as hungry, weird, or whimsical) have
added far more creativity in character creation and play.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Everything contains its opposite.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Dynamic Balance</title>
<para>
Essence: To survive, let alone to become powerful, one must keep every aspect
of one's universe(s) in a state of dynamic balance with every other one;
extremism is dangerous on both the personal and the evolutionary levels of
reality.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: Dance to the music.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Perversity</title>
<para>
Essence: Also known as Murphy's Law, Finagle's Law, etc.: if anything can go
wrong, it will - and in the most annoying manner possible.
</para>

<para>
Remarks: Magical associations sometimes operate in the reverse of what was
wanted; meaningful coincidences are just as likely to be unpleasant as they are
to be helpful (especially if a lot of emotion goes into the related situations).
Even if "nothing can possibly go wrong", some element of the universe may
change so that things will go wrong anyway.
</para>

<para>
This Law is probably based on the use of countermagic by one's own subconscious
mind, for whatever devious or even neurotic reasons it may have. My guess is
that it also ties in with the Anti-Psi talents. This Law explains why some
people's magic seems to work backwards. Emotionally healthy magicians have less
problems with this Law than unhealthy ones do, and once a magician has reached
the Master/Mistress rank his "klutz factor" tends to go down accordingly. The
klutz factor (or "fumble factor") is used by many referees to dampen down the
effectiveness of high-level magicians who are unbalancing their game universes,
but it has a basis in fact as well as in game playability.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: These can only be: If anything can go wrong, it will.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Law of Unity</title>
<para>
Essence: Every phenomenon in existence is linked directly or indirectly to
every other one, past, present or future; perceived separations between
phenomena are based on incomplete sensing and/or thinking.
</para>

<para>
Keywords: All is One.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Additional Notes on the Laws</title>
<para>
Several of these laws are obviously a part of the metaphysical background of
magic rather than part of its day-to-day techniques. Some, such as Invocation
and Evocation, or Infinite Universes and Personal Universes, may actually be
the same principles seen from different viewpoints. A few of the Laws usually
seem to be subsets or intersections of other laws, as the chart clearly shows.
</para>

<sect4><title>Similarity, Contagion &amp; The Golden Bough</title>
<para>
The best known of the laws in Western literature are Similarity and Contagion,
both of which are subsets of Association, and both of which are famous thanks
to the writings of Sir James Frazer, especially the multi-volume Golden Bough.
The one-volume edition, edited by T. Gaster and published under the name The
New Golden Bough, is well worth reading if you haven't the steam to go through
all 10,000+ pages of the original but you'll miss a lot of good stuff.
Many fictional and nonfictional works in occultism, fantasy and science fiction
(not to mention anthropology) published since Frazer's time blithely assume
that these two are the only laws involved in magic despite the fact that ample
evidence for the other laws is often present within these works themselves.
Apparently, few scholars care to credit "ignorant savages" and "primitive
ancestors" with being able to organize their observations into coherent systems
of thought, let alone into complex philosophies.
</para>

<para>
It should be remembered that similarities do not have to be visual ones, in
order to use the Law of Similarity. Sounds, smells, textures, tastes, etc. can
certainly be used, as well as abstract similarities that exist only in the mind
of the magician. As for Contagion, the phenomena involved do seem to have
falling-off patterns, or "half-lives". The longer it has been since the contact
was last made or used, the weaker the contagion link will be. But these sorts
of half-lives, represent far too delicate of a variable to worry about in game
magic, unless an individual referee may care to wing it on such judgements.
</para>

<para>
These Laws combine frequently. Blood from an aardvark can always be used to
control more aardvarks than the original donor, because aardvark blood will
always be very similar to aardvark blood. Control spells will work best on the
original source of the contagion sample (and parts of the body are usually the
best samples) but a body sample can always be used to boost the efficiency of a
spell done on any entity with a similar body (and this body does not always
have to be organic - a magician having problems with technological devices
might choose to carry transistors or wiring samples around).
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Invocations &amp; Evocations</title>
<para>
The Law of Invocation is the main law used by Shamans and other Mediums because
it deals with various types of possessions. The Law of Evocation, however, is
used by Goetic Magicians and Necromancers to summon various spirits, human or
nonhuman, many of which may be parts of the subconscious or superconscious
minds of the magicians themselves. However, the various spells used in
roleplaying games for Summoning Monsters have nothing to do with evoking them.
These spells actually seem to be methods for seeking out (via Telepathy or the
Clair-Senses) the nearest "monster" of the sort desired and of either helping
or forcing them to Teleport to the summoner.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Universe Hopping</title>
<para>
The Law of Infinite Universes could be used by magicians attempting to send an
object or being (including themselves) to another universe, or to retrieve
something or someone from another universe, as in various gateway spells.
While it is not mentioned by name, this law is actually the one used by the
protagonists to universe-hop in the (In-)Complete Enchanter series by Pratt
&amp; de Camp (who may have been the first folks to suggest using symbolic
logic equations to describe the Laws of Magic).
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Tactical Polarity</title>
<para>
The Law of Polarity can be used for tactical purposes in magical combat, since
every target is going to have a "weak spot" of some opposite characteristic
hidden deep within. Even the most stalwartly Good magician is going to have a
spot of Evil somewhere inside, though the higher his rank and the better his
emotional health, the weaker that spot will be (not only will it be harder to
get to, but it will be less useful to exploit).
</para>

<para>
The problem in most cases is to figure out just what constitutes the opposite
of a complex object or being. A Northern Fire Giant would have spots of
Southernliness, cold and dwarvishness inside his physical and psychic
structure, but only the cold spot would make a good flaw to concentrate upon in
most cases unless you could amplify his Southernliness to make him more
hospitable!
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Perversity &amp; Wishing</title>
<para>
The Law of Perversity can provide a number of amusing and infuriating incidents
in both real and game magic. In the occult community, one of the most popular
sayings around the world is "Always be careful what you ask for, you may get
it!" This leads into the subject of backfiring wishes, but wishes themselves
are such an irrational and absurd gimmick to throw into game magic systems that
it isn't even worth discussing them. They seem to be used mostly as a way to
cheat Fate and thus the game. The only magical excuse, explanation or plausible
reason for postulating the reality of the wishing phenomena is to assume that
there exist gigantically powerful mega-gods (probably of the Whimsical
alignment) who are contacted through the wishing devices and who delight in
performing full-scale miracles for (or to) stupid mortals. For those who insist
on wishing their characters out of every mess their bad play has caused, I have
only an old occult blessing: May your every wish come true.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Combining Laws</title>
<para>
As a matter of practical use, the Laws are seldom if ever applied in isolation.
Usually two or more are combined.
</para>

<para>
For example: a party of travelers is going through the wilderness when they
come upon a hostile dragon. Their only mage, Belinda the Befuddled, decides to
try a Command Dragon Spell, so she reaches into her pouch and pulls out a wand
made of dragon bone (Similarity) which is carved with the likeness of a dragon
(Similarity) and with several runes (Words of Power). One end is capped with a
dragon scale (Contagion, since she found it in the woods the previous night and
it actually belongs to the dragon in question, but it also works as Similarity)
and the other end is tipped with a crystal carved into the likeness of a dog's
paw (Similarity, to the deity about to be invoked). Calling upon the divine
name of Mighty Manfred the Dragon Slayer (Names, Invocation) the magician pulls
in extra mana from her deity, which she then sends forth with several Words of
Power in Auld Wurmish (a dragon language, and therefore more Similarity),
Mesmerically sending her commands to the dragon. Snarfblatt the Mighty promptly
forgets about his intention to eat the travelers and instead flies away to look
elsewhere for lunch. With great dignity, Belinda faints from relief.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>How the Laws Affect Spell Success</title>
<para>
There should be a way to add to a character's chances of success, when the
magician uses one or more of the Laws of Magic in the spell design. One way of
doing this is shown in the table below, in which particular uses of laws add
Possibility Increments (PIs) to any spell's Possibility of Spell Success (PoSS).
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
Using that system, Belinda the Befuddled got quite a bit of improvement
in her chances for success, with credit for using Similarity five times, Words
twice, and Contagion, Invocation &amp; Names once each. Even though she's only
using a single Psi Talent (Mesmerism) and probably couldn't have done it
without help from Mighty Manfred, still her multiple use of the Laws could
easily boost her success possibilities to her Magical Luck Limit for her rank.
</screen>
</informalexample>

<sect3><title>Effects of the Laws of Magic on Possibilities of Spell Success</title>
<para>
1: For every usage of a Law of Magic (except those listed below) in the casting
of a spell, add 1 to the PoSS. If the same Law is used more than once, add the
appropriate bonus for each usage.
</para>

<para>
2: For every usage of the Law of Similarity: add 1-4, depending upon the
degree of similarity involved.
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
Attempting to cast a spell on a gnome. Having a crude drawing of a dwarf
(another type of small humanoid) is barely worth 1. Having a coffeetable Book
of Gnomes is worth 2. Having a realistic painting of the gnome in question is
worth 3. If photographs are possible in the game universe involved, one might
push the bonus up to 4 for having a photo of the gnome.
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
3: For every usage of the Law of Contagion: add 1-5, depending upon the degree
of contagion involved.
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
Attempting to heal a damaged comrade from a distance. Having shaken hands with
her several times is barely worth 1. Having an item of her clothing or weapons
is worth 2. Having a lock of her hair is worth 3. Having kissed her a lot
recently, or having had more intense contact, may well be worth 4-5
depending on just how friendly you got! Being able to touch the target of a
spell during the casting period will usually add 2.
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
4: For every usage of the Law of Names: add 1 for using the target's "public
name", add 2 for using the target's "childhood name" or adult "pet name", add
3 for using the target's "secret name", and add 6 for using the target's
"true name". Target beings will usually know their own names in the first three
categories, but only a supernatural entity is liable to know their own or
someone else's "true name".
</para>

<para>
Note: An Invocation or Evocation bonus cancels out any connected Names bonus.
</para>

<para>
5: For every usage of the Law of Invocation or the Law of Evocation: add 1-4,
depending on one's own Piety; 1 for low Piety, 2 for average Piety, 3 for
high Piety, 4 for highest Piety. Some referees may prefer to use the
character's "State of Grace" for this.
</para>

<para>
6: For every usage of the Law of Perversity: add 3 if and only if Negapsi is
one of one's Gifts. Otherwise, subtract 3 or "crock" the results of the
spell. If the referee or the player determines that a given magician is
suffering a "streak of bad luck", expect the Law of Perversity (at referee's
option) to start making things even worse.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
