<sect1><title>Magic Skills</title>
<para>
There are two categories of magic skills in the DNet system. These are
source skills and conductor skills. For a character to successfully cast a
spell, he or she must successfully use source skills to make magical power
available, and then conductor skills to use that power.
</para>

<example><title>Skills For Fireball Spell</title>
<screen>
A magus' "Fireball" spell requires the caster to use
the "Elemental Power of Energy" source skill and then
the "Elemental Fire Focus" conductor skill.
</screen>
</example>

<para>
Thus, the character must succeed on two task resolutions: the first to gather
the necessary magical energy (source), and the second to use the energy made
available (conductor).
</para>

<sect2><title>Sources</title>
<para>
Source skills represent the ability of the caster to draw upon a particular
source of supernatural energy and make that energy available for the casting
of a spell. Sources are much like outlets in the modern world. Outlets are
useless by themselves, but when their energy is used by an appliance,
technological wonders occur. So, too, are source skills useless by themselves,
but when their energy is used by a conductor skill, magic happens.
</para>

<para>
Whenever a caster wishes to cast a spell, he must make the energy for that
spell available by using one or more source skills. Making the energy
available is a simple matter of making a  task check using the source skill
required of the spell at the Source Task Difficulty (TD) of the spell.
</para>

<example><title>Source Skill For Fireball Spell</title>
<screen>
The "Fireball" spell has a Source TD of 13 and to use that spell
the caster must first make the Source task check:

   d10-d10* + "Elemental Power of Energy" Skill &gt;= 13
</screen>
</example>

<para>
If the task check fails, the caster is unable to gather the energy required
for the spell and the spell fizzles. If the composite task check succeeds,
the character has successfully gathered the energy, and may proceed to
harness that energy using the appropriate conductor skill.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Conductors</title>
<para>
Where source skills represent an ability to draw upon a particular source of
supernatural energy, conductor skills represent an ability to use that energy
in a particular way. Where a source skill is an outlet in the modern world, a
conductor is an appliance. Without electricity, appliances are useless by
themselves, but when they are given energy to work with they can do amazing
things. So, too, are conductor skill useless without energy from a source
skill, but when they have that energy, magic happens.
</para>

<para>
We must also take the analogy one step further. Not all appliances can plug
into all outlets throughout the world; they must have compatible voltages and
have the same type of current. Conductors, too, can only be used with those
sources with which they are compatible. Energy from any other incompatible
source is useless to them. The sources with which a given conductor is
compatible are listed in the description for that skill.
</para>

<para>
Once a caster has gathered the energy from a source, he or she can utilize
that energy by using a conductor skill. Similar to using source skills,
harnessing and shaping energy using conductor skills is a simple matter of
making a task check using the conductor skill required of the spell at the
Conductor Task Difficulty (TD) of the spell.
</para>

<example><title>Conductor Skill For Fireball Spell</title>
<screen>
The "Fireball" spell from above has a Conductor TD of 5 which uses the "Elemental Fire Focus" conductor.
Therefore, to finish casting this spell (once energy has been made available from the appropriate source),
the caster must make this task check:

     d10-d10* + "Elemental Fire Focus" Skill &gt;= 5
</screen>
</example>

<para>
If the composite task check fails, the caster was unable to successfully
conduct the spell's energy and an unpredictable result may occur; the power
was not properly "focused." Once the conductor task check has succeeded, the
spell is cast.
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Optionally, a failure of the source check can cause damage to the caster.
</emphasis>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Source Skill List</title>
<para>
<table frame="all"><title>Source Skills</title>
<tgroup cols="5" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="5" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Skill Name</entry><entry>BC</entry><entry>Tal*</entry><entry>Adv</entry><entry>Compatible Conductor(s)</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Celestial Power of Darkness</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Celestial Foci</entry></row>
<row><entry>Celestial Power of Daylight</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Celestial Foci</entry></row>
<row><entry>Elemental Power of Energy</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Elemental Foci</entry></row>
<row><entry>Elemental Power of Entropy</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Elemental Foci</entry></row>
<row><entry>Kundalini</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>the Chackras</entry></row>
<row><entry>Spirit of [spirit]</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>AUR</entry><entry>AUR</entry><entry>Communion with Spirits</entry></row>
<row><entry>Doctrine of [deity]</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>PSY</entry><entry>PSY</entry><entry>Piety to [same deity]</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
*All Sources have an UP of Impossible.
</para>

<formalpara><title>Celestial Power of Darkness</title>
<para>
The Celestial Power of Darkness is one of the two Celestial Powers, those
source skills used by Celestial Magi. This particular source allows a
magus to call upon 'negative' magical energy to use with the Celestial
Foci, those conductor skills compatible with the Celestial Powers and used
by Celestial Magi. Darkness, when used with a Celestial Focus, destroys or
diminishes that which falls under the purview of that Focus. The Power of
Darkness is not an evil power, as many seem to believe, it is simply one
of the destructive powers of the universe.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Celestial Power of Daylight</title>
<para>
The Celestial Power of Daylight is the 'positive' Celestial Power. It is
used to build up and enhance in ways depending upon which aspect of the
power the magus chooses to focus into form and reality.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Elemental Power of Energy</title>
<para>
The Power of Energy plays the role for Elemental Magi that the Power of
Daylight plays for Celestial Magi. This power creates, enhances, and
builds up the elements.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Elemental Power of Entropy</title>
<para>
The Power of Entropy is the opposite of the Power of Energy. Its role is
similar to that of the Power of Darkness of the Celestial Magi. It tears
down, destroys, and subdues the elements under its control. It is the
unrelenting force in the universe that will not rest until all is
destroyed. Again, this Power is not evil inherently, only when used for
evil deeds.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Kundalini</title>
<para>
Kundalini is the raw energy which exists in the Astral Plane. The Psionic
draws upon Kundalini and uses it through different Chakras (the associated
conductors) to achieve different effects. The Psionic is more versatile
than the Magi, but less powerful at manipulating his reality. None surpass
the Psionic's mastery of the mind, however.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Spirit of spirit</title>
<para>
The Spirit world is the domain of the Shamanic spell-caster. For each type
of Spirit the Shaman wishes to contact and commune with, the Shaman must
have a Source skill. After the Spirit has been contacted using this Source
skill, the Shaman must commune with the Spirit using the Communion
conductor skill to attempt to explain to the Spirit what is desired, and
to convince the Spirit to do as it is asked.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Doctrine of deity</title>
<para>
The power of the gods is available to those who call themselves Priests.
Priests worship one (or, rarely, more) deity who answers his Priests'
prayers and requests in the form of Miracles (spells). In order to have
one's prayers heard by a deity, the Priest must have a skill in that
deity's Doctrine. This skill represents how well the Priest knows the
teachings and requirements of the deity necessary to get part of the
deity's attention. The higher the character's skill in Doctrine, the
greater portion of the deity's attention is gained. Once the Priest has
successfully contacted the deity with a Doctrine skill, he must pray the
the deity does as he wishes, the success of which is determined by the
Priest's Piety skill to that deity.
</para>
</formalpara>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Conductor Skill List</title>
<para>
<table frame="all"><title>Conductor Skills</title>
<tgroup cols="5" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="5" colname="c5" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<spanspec spanname="hspan" namest="c1" nameend="c5" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Skill Name</entry><entry>BC</entry><entry>Tal*</entry><entry>Adv</entry><entry>Compatible Source(s)</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Air Elemental Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Elemental Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry>Earth Elemental Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Elemental Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry>Fire Elemental Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Elemental Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry>Water Elemental Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Elemental Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry>5th Elemental Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Elemental Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry spanname="hspan"></entry></row>
<row><entry>Aurora Celestial Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Celestial Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry>Comet Celestial Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Celestial Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry>Firmament Celestial Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Celestial Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry>Light Celestial Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Celestial Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry>Moon Celestial Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Celestial Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry>Stars Celestial Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Celestial Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry>Sun Celestial Focus</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>INT</entry><entry>the Celestial Powers</entry></row>
<row><entry spanname="hspan"></entry></row>
<row><entry>Astral Chackra</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>Kundalini</entry></row>
<row><entry>Body Chackra</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>Kundalini</entry></row>
<row><entry>Dream Chackra</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>Kundalini</entry></row>
<row><entry>Emotion Chackra</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>Kundalini</entry></row>
<row><entry>ESP Chackra</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>Kundalini</entry></row>
<row><entry>Mind Chackra</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>Kundalini</entry></row>
<row><entry>Reality Chackra</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>Kundalini</entry></row>
<row><entry>Temporal Chackra</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>WIL</entry><entry>Kundalini</entry></row>
<row><entry spanname="hspan"></entry></row>
<row><entry>Piety to [deity]</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>AUR</entry><entry>AUR</entry><entry>Doctrine of [same deity]</entry></row>
<row><entry>Communion with Spirits</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>PSY</entry><entry>PSY</entry><entry>Spirit of [any spirit]</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
*All Conductors have an UP of Impossible.
</para>

<formalpara><title>Elemental Air Focus</title>
<para>
The focus of air is the ethereal aspect of the elemental powers. It
controls winds and gravity. With the energy of air, a magus can fly above
his enemies, or blow thunderstorms over their heads. The entropy of air
can cause suffocation of his enemies, or bring things down to earth.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Elemental Earth Focus</title>
<para>
The earth is the focus of physical power. This aspect of energy affects all
things with solid physical form. With this power the magus may raise up
great mountains, or bring them crashing down upon his foes. The earth
aspect of entropy allows the magus to destroy the physical. With it he can
disintegrate physical objects and beings, or create doorways where none
were before.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Elemental Fire Focus</title>
<para>
Fire is the form of true power. Fire is heat, warmth, life, and energy. By
mastering the aspect of fire, a magus can hurl balls of flame towards his
enemies, or keep warm on a cold winters night. He can cause forest-fires
in the dead of winter, or light a dark passage. Using entropy, the magus
can hurl balls of ice, or stamp out natural or magical flames, or even put
out the fire within each person.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Elemental Water Focus</title>
<para>
The water focus is the domain of the seas and the lakes. It has complete
control over liquids in all its forms. It can bring water into being for
the benefit of the magus, or drown the magus' enemies. It can also create
patches of ice, or slippery stones. The entropy aspect of this focus
destroys water, soaks it up. This aspect can turn an enemy into parched
dry bones instantly, or dry up a lake which happens to be in the way.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>The 5th Elemental Focus</title>
<para>
Powerful Elemental Magi have theorized the existence of a 5th Element of
unknown properties which could be used with the Energy or Entropy sources
of Elemental magic. Unfortunately, no one has yet discovered this elusive
Element, or determined its probable nature. Perhaps the sages of DnExotica
will, in time, solve this perplexing mystery :).
</para>
</formalpara>

<para>
Current theories include the concept of an Element of Nothingness, or Void,
an Element of Pure Magic, an Element of Spirit, an Element of the Aether,
that which fills the Void, or a Quintessential Element. It is believed that
once the 5th Element is discovered, many of the mysteries of Elemental magic
will be solved.
</para>

<formalpara><title>Celestial Aurora Focus</title>
<para>
The aurora, which appears in the northern night sky, is the most beautiful
and entrancing of all celestial elements. Through the study of this
wondrous effect, magi are able to draw upon and use its ability to charm
and entrance the observer. With this focus, the magus may charm an enemy
and calm his friends. With the darkness of the aurora, a magus may strike
fear into his enemy, remove charmed influences from his friends, and
prevent beguiling effects from manipulating himself or others.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Celestial Comet Focus</title>
<para>
The comet is the messenger of the heavens. Continually moving at blinding
speeds throughout the night sky, it is the master of all movement. By
studying the properties of the comet, the magus is able to use its
movement for himself. With this focus he can instantly move anywhere in
the world, or, in combination with the focus of the firmament, he can even
move out of this world. The darkness of the comet prevents movement,
imprisoning and trapping enemies, and preventing others from coming near.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Celestial Firmament Focus</title>
<para>
The light of the sky and the heavens above is the study of the firmament.
Those magi who strive to understand the magnitude of the firmament, are
able to transcend this reality and get a glimpse into other realities of
infinite varieties. Through this study, magi can commune with gods or
angels or demons. In combination with the field of comet, magi are even
able to walk the infinite planes of existence. Through the study of the
night sky, the darkness of the heavens, magi are able to block off the
conduits through which these inter-planar communion occur. With this
discipline, magi can return foreigners to their home realities, and
prevent their return, or stop the communication of other magi with
extra-planar beings.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Celestial Light Focus</title>
<para>
Light is purity incarnate. This focus allows the magus to wield true power,
without manipulation. With it bolts of pure magical energy can spring
forth from the casters hand, or magical effects can be detected or
enhanced. The dark allows the magus to cancel the magic of others or
inhibit magic.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Celestial Moon Focus</title>
<para>
The moon is the mistress of mysteries, the lady of the night. Under her
pale glow, reality takes on new dimension. By studying the moon, magi are
able to use her light to mask reality, to make what isn't really there
come to life. With this power, magi can weave strange and powerful
illusions of things which only exist by the light of the moon, though the
moon does not need to actually be shining for the magus to draw upon her
power. Those who study the dark side of the moon, on the other hand, can
see through all pretenses and appearances to the stark reality underneath,
though the vision is not always a pleasant one. Illusions have no affect
on those who wield the power of the dark side of the moon, and all that
was once hidden comes clear.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Celestial Stars Focus</title>
<para>
The stars in their infinite formations hold the knowledge of all that was,
all that is, and all that will be. Through the study of starlight, the
magus can glean some small inkling into the vastness of the universe and
can divine what is and what will come. Through knowledge of the light of
the stars, all knowledge comes clear. However, by manipulating the dark
stars, magi are able to obscure the meaning the stars hold. They can
prevent less powerful magi from discerning particular knowledge, or even
misdirect such inquiries.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Celestial Sun Focus</title>
<para>
The sun is the giver of life, the celestial orb that brings warmth and
health to all the realms. Therefore, the sun is the focus of life. The
celestial magus who masters the sun aspect of daylight masters life
itself. He is capable of healing, or even of bringing those which were
dead back to the realms of the living. However, the one who masters the
darkness aspect of the sun learn the true meaning of death, and with that
knowledge can bring death to others and undo the work of the sun.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Astral Chakra</title>
<para>
This is the Chakra that allows the Psionic that in addition to the normal
capabilities of drawing power from the Astral Dimension, allows the
Psionic to also travel into this dimension and to summon creatures from
the Astral dimension.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Body Chakra</title>
<para>
Man is not made of only a mind, but also a physical body. Through the use
of this Chakra, the Psionic can utilize the Astral energy to enhance his
physical attributes.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Dream Chakra</title>
<para>
This powerful Chakra allows the Psionic to achieve superhuman feats, as he
accomplishes them not in this world, but the world of his dreams. Of
course, the unnaturally good is tempered with the unnaturally bad--most
Dream powers carry some penalty, as they are under control of the Psionic
subconscious, and not his conscious mind.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Emotion Chakra</title>
<para>
This Chakra deals with the emotional, colorful side of the mind, whereas
Mind deals with the cold, logical side of the mind.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>ESP Chakra</title>
<para>
Clairvoyance, reading the future, picking up auras would be included in
this Chakra. It would also affect how much the psionic can perceive while
in the astral plane.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Mind Chakra</title>
<para>
The Psionic's most powerful tool is his mind. Utilizing the Chakras of mind
allows the Psionic not only to delve deeper into his mind than he normally
would be capable of doing, but it also allows him to delve into the mind
of others when it is used in conjunction with other Chakras.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Reality Chakra</title>
<para>
This Chakra is about imposing a Psionic's will over reality. Control over
Fire, Air, Water, and Earth would be included in this Chakra. A psionic
wouldn't be able to manipulate these elements as well as an elemental
magus. An example of this Chakra would be a fire-starter (pyrogenic).
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Temporal Chakra</title>
<para>
This Chakra would be allow the psionic to affect the flow of time and to
perceive in things in the future and/or past. Examples of this would be
(in conjunction with other Chakras) slowing down metabolism, fortune
telling, speeding healing, etc.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Piety to deity</title>
<para>
The Piety skills represent how devout and reverent a character has learned
to act towards a particular deity. Because the nature of worship required
by separate deities is different, there is a unique Piety skill for each
deity. Pragmatically, the Piety skills are what keep Priests on the 'good'
sides of their deities. That is to say, the Piety skill helps to convince
the deity to act in the best interests of the Priest, after the Priest has
gotten part of the deity's attention, instead of, say, killing the priest. :)
</para>
</formalpara>

<para>
Because the Priest must be able to gain a part of the deity's attention
before making his request, the Priest must first have at least 1 level of
training in the Doctrine skill of a deity before he may be trained in the
Piety skill of that deity.
</para>

<formalpara><title>Communion with Spirits</title>
<para>
The Communion conductor is what allows those who weave Shamanic spells to
commune with the denizens of the Spirit world. It is this communion which
allows the caster to communicate to the Spirits his or her desires.
Without this, the Spirits would be powerless to help the caster. The skill
level a caster possesses in the Communion skill represents how capable the
caster is of communicating complex wishes to Spirits.
</para>
</formalpara>

<para>
Before using the Communion skill, the caster must first contact the Spirit
with which he wishes to commune using the appropriate Spirit skill, and he
must, therefore, have some skill in a Spirit skill before gaining training
in the Communion skill.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
