<sect1><title>Parapsychology, the Apologetic Science</title>
<para>
The people who have studied psi phenomena and powers quickly
divided everything into two categories: Extrasensory Perception
and Paraphysics (thats "mind over matter"). I have added a third
category: Hypercognition ("super fast thinking"), plus a new area
called Anti-Psi for the barbarians.
</para>

<sect2><title>Extrasensory Perception</title>
<para>
      Extrasensory Perception is the reception of data without using
      the normal sense channels.
</para>

<sect3><title>Telepathy</title>
<para>
        Telepathy: the direct communication of data between minds. The
        data may be pictures, ideas, sensations, or emotions. The
        simpler the message, the more likely it is to get through and
        the greater distance it will go. As a rule, emotions and
        associations travel best. Derived from Greek "far-sensing."
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>General Extrasensory Perception</title>
<para>
        GESP: together, the clair-senses are called GESP, or General
        ExtraSensory Perceptions.
</para>

<sect4><title>Clairvoyance</title>
<para>
        Clairvoyance: the reception of data which seems visual without
        the medium of another mind. A common type of clairvoyance is
        when you seem to see an image of a person or thing in your
        room. Often this image is connected with sudden death. This is
        called a "veridical hallucination" by some. Derived from the
        French "clear-seeing."
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Clairaudience</title>
<para>
        Clairaudience: is data input as normal sound even though the
        actual hearing of sound is impossible. Most spontaneous
        clairaudience takes the form of hearing "voices" or "sounds"
        connected with recent death or tragedy. Also derived from the
        French "clear-hearing."
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Clairgustance</title>
<para>
        Clairgustance: as above but using the sense of taste.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Clairolfaction</title>
<para>
        Clairolfaction: as above but using the sense of smell.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Clairtangency</title>
<para>
        Clairtangency: as above but using the sense or touch.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Clairempathy</title>
<para>
        Clairempathy: most people say that a place or object has good
        or bad "vibrations" and leave it at that. A haunted house, for
        example, usually has some pretty heavy "vibes." When
        clairempathy is limited to objects, it is often called
        "psychometry," a term we will not use.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>The Total Empath</title>
<para>
        The Total Empath: is someone is simply absorbs the local
        "atmosphere" wherever he may be. Sometimes called "sensitives"
        these people are as a rule totally defenseless against psychic
        attack or even undirected strong emotion in their vicinity.
        They tend to die young, from emotional exhaustion, or wind up
        in mental institutions.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Psychic Vampires</title>
<para>
        Psychic Vampires: Some empaths can control this absorption and
        literally drain others of their psychic energy. Sometimes
        known when habitually irresponsible as "psychic vampires".
        These people are on the border of Extrasensory Perception and
        Anti-Psi.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Astral &amp; Mental Projection</title>
<para>
        Astral &amp; Mental Projection: these are defined as being GESP
        combined with concepts of "travelling" either through normal
        space or through various "astral planes." The difference
        between the types of projection is that in astral projecting
        you hallucinate the image of a slightly translucent body,
        called the "astral body", which rises from your physical body
        and carries your center of consciousness with it. In those
        rare instances when the agent has a maimed or crippled body,
        his astral body is usually perfect and unblemished. The famous
        "silver cord" that shows up often, but not always, in astral
        projection is basically an umbilical one connecting the navel
        of the astral body to the navel of the physical one. This cord
        can grow to be almost infinite length. Some experienced agents
        talk about looping the cord around trees or telephone poles to
        anchor themselves. Should your silver cord be cut, many claim,
        you would surely perish. Mental projection is said to be
        easier than astral projection and the reason is, I think, that
        agent actually generates his astral body and silver cord to
        comfort him in his fear that he might be seperated permanently
        from his physical body. As for the argument that astral bodies
        have been photographed, I suggest that that strong-willed
        person is using some Paraphysic talent to further enhance his
        astral body.
</para>

<para>
        Though many occultists today consider "astral planes" to be
        simply various parts of the mind, to the agent these planes
        are completely real and solid to his astral body. If an agent
        were to meet another agent upon these planes, both are capable
        of damaging eachother's astral body, damage which is firmly
        believed to be reflected on the physical body.
</para>

<para>
        Most personifications which the agent meets during astral
        projection are patterns within his own metapattern, and we all
        have some pretty nasty demons locked up in our subconscious.
        An agent who meets another actual agent in the astral plane is
        probably using the astral planes as an input device for
        telepathy.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Animal Psi</title>
<para>
        Animal Psi: involves many different phenomena of unusual
        nature either occuring between humans and animals or between
        animals and animals or animals alone. Some of these are
        familiar to all of us; the dog or cat that travels thousands
        of miles to find his home after being lost; the dog who howls
        at his master's death, and so forth. Some laboratory
        experiments have been done which demonstrate the occasional
        use of telepathy between humans and animals.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Plant Psi</title>
<para>
        Plant Psi: got its greatest publicity when a researcher
        decided to hook an EEG machine to some plants and record their
        reactions when he injured tissue by slicing or burning. He
        found that he didn't have to actually touch the plants to
        cause a reaction, the mere though ot hurting the plant caused
        the needle to swing wildly.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Paraphysics</title>
<para>
      Paraphysics are types of psi involving apparently mental control
      over matter.
</para>

<sect3><title>Pyschokinesis</title>
<para>
        Pyschokinesis: the psi talent having the most laboratory
        evidence accumulated in its favor, it seems to have been shown
        that people can move matter and control what should be the
        random movement of small objects such as dice. When an object
        or person floats across the room, this form of PK is called
        levitation. This has some connection with the traditional
        skills of Eastern adepts in making objects heavier or lighter,
        something we would call Mass Control.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Teleportation &amp; Apportation</title>
<para>
        Teleportation &amp; Apportation: are the instant moving of people
        and things (respectively) from one point to another without
        going throught space as we know it. Teleportation has been
        done only in fiction, myth, and scripture, though sufficient
        enough to raise suspicion. Apportation has been done in the
        laboratory. Living creatures which were apported always died.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Atomic PK</title>
<para>
        Atomic PK: the use of PK upon matter at molecular, atomic, and
        subatomic levels. As we shall see, the smaller the object, the
        easier it is use PK on it. Thus there is no reason not to
        extend PK on down to these levels. Some types of APK are:
</para>

<sect4><title>Transmutation</title>
<para>
          Transmutation: the alteration of the basic structure of
          matter by rearranging electrons, protons, nuetrons, and so
          on. Changing water to wine or lead to gold would be
          transmutation instead of "miracle" or "alchemy."
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Psychopyresis</title>
<para>
          Psychopyresis: the igniting and control of fires, done by
          speeding up atoms with APK.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Psycholuminescence</title>
<para>
          Psycholuminescence: the control of photons and thus of
          light. This could account for halos, auras, mysterious
          lights, and a host of similar phenomena. From occult
          literature, it would seem that Psycholuminescence is the
          easiest form of APK to do. This probably has something to do
          with the fact that the photon is one of the smallest known
          subatomic particles.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Weather Control</title>
<para>
          Weather Control: the moving of large amounts of air
          molecules and maybe water molecules, around. Much easier to
          do where the weather is less stable.
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Cellular PK</title>
<para>
        Cellular PK: the use of PK on living cells. People can be
        killed by curses without knowing that they have been cursed.
        People have been cured of genuine physical diseases at places
        like Fatima and Lourdes, as well as by local witch doctors.
        Hypnosis has been used to speed up the rate of cell regrowth
        in damaged tissue, healing burned skin, for example, in two or
        three days; without leaving scars. Spontaneous cures in cancer
        are almost always associated with a change in attitude on the
        part of the patient, who simply refuses to die. There is a
        phenomena I call CPK Assimilation in which the healer exhibits
        the the same symptoms as the patient for a short time, after
        which the disease vanishes from healer and patient alike. The
        Pomo Shamaness Essie Parrish contracted arthritis and diabetes
        this way.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Recurrent Spontaneous PK</title>
<para>
        Recurrent Spontaneous PK: the cause of what are normally
        called "poltergeists" or "noisy ghosts." Almost all RSPK
        activity involves the movement of objects through space; the
        rest are matters of RS-APK where objects explode or implode.
        The move- ment of objects during RSPK form a "Vortex Field,"
        known in mathematics as the "Exponential Decay Function,"
        which is a formula for describing the conversion of energy
        from one form to another. In this case, it seems, the Vortex
        Field describes the conversion of Psychic energy to Kinetic
        energy.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Hypercognition</title>
<para>
      Hypercognition: superfast reasoning, often using data received
      via ESP, usually at the subconscious or unconscious level,
      resulting in an accurate statement and presented to the
      conscious mind as "flash" of "inspiration" or as a "hunch." If
      you do this and arrive at a statement about the future, it is
      called Precognition, about the past and it is called
      Retrocognition.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Anti-Psi</title>
<para>
      Anti-Psi: this is the realm of those talents that frustrate,
      avoid, destroy, or generally mess up regular psi talents.
</para>

<sect3><title>Catapsi</title>
<para>
        Catapsi: the generation of "static" that cancels out psi
        powers within its range. It seems that the rabidly
        skeptical person is usually pretty good at generated
        prodigout amounts of Catapsi. Catapsi is the psychic
        equivalent of "white noise," energy being broadcast in
        random patterns, blocking coherent ones.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Splodging</title>
<para>
        Splodging: a widespread general broadcasting of emotion so
        strong that is drowns out all other competing psi, and so
        strong that it even normally untalented people can pick it
        up. It usually occurs in anxiety states, and the Splodger
        is rarely aware of the fact that he is doing it. It has
        been called the equivalent of the "Psychic Yell" and often
        makes its recipient quite uncomfortable.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Apopsi</title>
<para>
        Apopsi: this is the talent for being completely immune to
        any psi activity directed toward one. These people are the
        exact opposites of The Total Empath. Just as the Catapsi-er
        tends to have a hostile personality, the Apopsi-er tends to
        have a very withdrawn, unemotional nature.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Negapsi</title>
<para>
        Negapsi: the "reversal" of any psi activity in the vicinity.
        If you are blessing a Negapsi-er it turns to a curse, and a
        curse to a blessing. If he tried to do Precognition it turns
        out to be Retrocognition. If he tries to score high on an
        ESP test, he score BELOW average.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Reddopsi</title>
<para>
        Reddopsi: this is the ability to instantly return any psi
        aimed at you back to the point of its origin. If someone
        tries to curse a Reddopsi-er the curse will simply be sent
        right back to the curser, often without the Reddopsi-er
        consciously realizing it.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
