<sect1><title>Magic Spells</title>
<para>
The casting of magic spells is the primary task to which source and conductor
skills are put. The variety in types of spells is as infinite as a player's
imagination. Spell effects may be small or large, blatant or subtle. Types of
spells range from powers of the mind to pyrotechnics of the skies. Yet even
with all of these differences, there are some basic rules and guidelines
governing the creation and use of spells in the DNet system.
</para>

<sect2><title>Casting Spells</title>
<para>
Casting a spell operates just like any other task in the DNet system with
two minor exceptions:
</para>

<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<para>
Successful spellcasting requires two consecutive, successful 
       task checks: the first to make the energy available to the caster,
       using source skill(s), and the second to harness that available energy
       using conductor skill(s). No conductor check is needed if the source
       check is failed
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Secondly, spellcasting is much more tiring work than most activities. 
       To reflect this, the caster's fatigue heap is incremented by one plus 
       one fifth of the Source TD the spell the caster attempts to cast. If 
       the spell fails, the caster only suffers from half the normal Fatigue 
       increase.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
Other differences may occur beyond those mentioned above, depending on the
spellcaster(s), the spell(s), and the skill(s) involved.
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
For example, some conductor skills require spells to be researched
or otherwise learned before they can be used.
</screen>
</informalexample>

<para>
In the standard rules, no spell requires any spell component, obvious
incantation or specific gesture. It is not meant that such requirement are
inappropriate, only that their application is left to the game master. Some
optional rules that integrate those elements may be included with the
standard rules in the future.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Spell Attributes</title>
<para>
All spells have many of the same basic attributes. These attributes bear no
relation to a character's attributes, except in that they serve to define the
basic nature of the spell in the same way that character attributes serve to
define the basic nature of a character. The basic attributes and their values
are:
</para>

<formalpara><title>Source(s)</title>
<para>
    Each spell must also define which source(s) of energy are used to draw the
    power required by the spell.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Source TD</title>
<para>
    The total TD associated with gathering the energy from the source(s).
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Conductor(s)</title>
<para>
    Each spell must also define which conductor(s) must be used to harness the
    energy once it is gathered from the source(s).
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Conductor TD</title>
<para>
   The total TD associated with making use of the conductors.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Fatigue</title>
<para>
    The Fatigue created by the spell.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Casting Time</title>
<para>
    This value represents the amount of time it takes to successfully cast the
    spell. This value is the Conductor TD of the spell, in seconds.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Duration</title>
<para>
    This value represents the length of time the spell lasts once it has been
    successfully cast.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Range</title>
<para>
    This value represents the maximum distance, in meters, from the caster that
    the spell effect may be centered or initiated.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Volume of Effect</title>
<para>
    This value represents the volume of space which is directly affected by the
    casting of this spell. (Note that secondary effects, like falling rocks,
    may extend beyond this range.)
</para>
</formalpara>

<para>
Spell descriptions may augment or supersede this list of attributes.
</para>

<sect3><title>Sample Spell</title>
<para>
Fireball

<screen>
Source: Elemental Power of Energy
Conductor: Elemental Fire Focus
Source TD: 13
Conductor TD: 5
Fatigue: 4
Casting time: 2 rounds (10 seconds)
Duration: 1 round
Range: 40 meters
Volume of Effect. A sphere with a radius of 5 meters

Allows the mage to create a ball of fire of 10m radius at up to 40m from the
caster. Any person within the ball must make an AGI roll against a TD of 5
to receive only half damage. The fire causes 2d6+1 of damage to anyone who
misses the resistance roll. The center of the fireball is located at most 1
meter from the area determined by the mage.
</screen>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Making Spells</title>
<para>
The procedure and rules used for making a new spell are entirely dependent
upon the types of conductor skills to be used by the Spell. Some conductors
require research and memorization, some require learning, others allow for
'on-the-fly' creation. Please see the conductor skill lists for specific
rules.
</para>

<para>
Standard spell creation rules have been designed for use with the magic
rules presented in this chapter. They  mainly consist in a set of standard
tables designed to calculate the Source and Conductor Task Difficulties. All
spells provided with the DNET system have been created using those tables
and all spells submitted will see their Source and Conductor TD evaluated
using them. You are free to ignore them completely if you find them too
cumbersome.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title><emphasis>Tweaking Spells (VERY OPTIONAL)</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>Note: All the material presented in this section is optional.</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
The ability to tweak a spell allows a spellcaster to modify one or more of
the basic attributes of a spell, or (depending on the spell) some of the
specific effects of the spell.
</emphasis>
</para>

<example><title><emphasis>Tweaking Spells</emphasis></title>
<screen>
<emphasis>
Putting more energy into a simple "Fireball" spell can increase
the damage it does, which is not a basic attribute.
</emphasis>
</screen>
</example>

<para>
<emphasis>
For those spellcasters restricted to previously learned or researched spells,
the ability to tweak those spells they already know is a godsend. However, the
degree to which spells may be tweaked is limited, as are the ways in which they
may be tweaked.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
When a caster tweaks a spell, he changes an aspect of the spell result by
changing either the Source TD, Conductor TD or both. Which aspects of a
spell may be tweaked, and to what degree at what cost, are generally
specific to the spell being cast. However, there are two general 'tweaks'
which should be available to almost all casters and for almost all spells:
</emphasis>
</para>

<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>
The fatigue caused by a spell may be reduced by using more finesse.
       For every point by which the Source TD is decreased, the Conductor
       TD is increased by 2. Fatigue and casting time are adjusted to 
       reflect the changes.
</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
  
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>
The casting time of a spell may be reduced by using more brute force.
       For every point by which the Conductor TD is decreased, the Source 
       TD is increased by 2. Fatigue and casting time are adjusted to 
       reflect the changes.
</emphasis>
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
<emphasis>
Almost all other 'tweaks' change the Source or Conductor TD (and subsequently
both the casting time and the fatigue incurred) of the spell.
Examples of aspects of a spell which might be capable of being tweaked in
this way include:
</emphasis>
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Duration</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Range</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Volume of Effect</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Damage</emphasis></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
<emphasis>
If the game master is very familiar with the magic system, he can guess the
variations in Source and Conductor TD on the fly when a mage attempts to
tweak a spell. Otherwise, it is suggested to use the spell creation tables
from the standard spell creation system.
</emphasis>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
