<sect1><title><emphasis>Graded Outcome (Optional)</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
For GMs who prefer a slightly less absolute (success or failure) system of
determining the result of Task Resolution, the following system is provided
as an option for measuring the degree of success or failure.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<table frame="all"><title><emphasis>Graded Outcome</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="2" align="center">
<colspec column="1" colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec column="2" colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<tbody>
<row><entry><emphasis>Bonus</emphasis></entry>  <entry><emphasis><literal>roll &gt;= TD + 10</literal></emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Success</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis><literal>TD &lt;= roll &lt;= TD + 9</literal></emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Partial</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis><literal>TD - 4 &lt;= roll &lt;= TD - 1</literal></emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Failure</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis><literal>TD - 9 &lt;= roll &lt;= TD - 5</literal></emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Mishap</emphasis></entry> <entry><emphasis><literal>roll &lt;= TD - 10</literal></emphasis></entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</para>

<formalpara><title><emphasis>Bonus</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
A really good outcome which surpasses normal expectations.
If the GM cannot think of a reasonable Bonus then the outcome should simply be
treated as a Success.
</emphasis>
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title><emphasis>Success</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
A successful outcome which achieves the desired result.
</emphasis>
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title><emphasis>Partial</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
An outcome that could be categorized as somewhere between Success and Failure.
The exact result is left to GM discretion.
</emphasis>
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title><emphasis>Failure</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
An unsuccessful outcome which does not achieve the desired result.
</emphasis>
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title><emphasis>Mishap</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
A particularly bad failure that exposes the character to additional misfortune,
harm, penalty or confusion. If the GM cannot think of a reasonable Mishap then
the outcome should simply be treated as a Failure.
</emphasis>
</para>
</formalpara>

<para>
<example><title><emphasis>Graded Outcome</emphasis></title>
<screen>
<emphasis>
Shardra the Ranger has Tracking 4. She tries picking up the trail of a
wounded bandit. The GM decides that this will be hard, as it's been raining.
The Task Resolution formula becomes:

d10-d10* + 4 &gt;= 5

If Shardra's player's total roll is 15 or higher, a Bonus, not only does
Shardra pick up the trail, she also picks up the overlying trail of a
pursuing wolverine.

If she rolls 5 to 14, a Success, Shardra picks up the bandit's trail.

If she rolls 1 to 4, a Partial, Shardra only picks up enough of the trail
to determine the general direction taken by the bandit.

If she rolls -4 to 0, a Failure, Shardra is unable to pick up the trail
because it has been washed away.

If she rolls a -5 or less, a Mishap, Shardra picks up the wrong trail that
leads her in a totally different direction.
</emphasis>
</screen>
</example>
</para>
</sect1>
