<sect1>
<title>Backgrounds</title>
<para>
Backgrounds are like Gifts and Flaws only they relate more to a
character's history rahter than to a character's abilities.
</para>

<para>
Freeform text is a fairly good way of describing a characters background.
Would it be even better to combine it with predetermened backgrounds
as in the Storyteller system?
</para>

<para>
<screen>
Ex:
Bloodline (depending on definition, could be a Gift or Flaw or both)
Bloodline, Planetouched - Someone of your ancestors where not human.
Resources
Social Status/Influence
Allies
Enemies
Secret Identity
Contacts
Devine Spark - the Spark of the upper planes; potential God? Wherever you thread, light follows. Easily recognized for what you are.
Infernal Taint - the Taint of Evil runs through your vains. Darkness surrounds you. Intimidating. You spread fear. Easily recognized for what you are.
</screen>
</para>

<!--
<para>
Not to be confused with Gifts and Flaws! Or could Backgrounds just be
Gifts or Flaws related to a characters history?
</para>
-->

<para>
Backgrounds should be characteristics relating to characters, to characters
history, etc.
Where Gifts and Flaws are [internal] characteristics of a character,
Backgrounds are [external] characteristics.
Gifts and Flaws are inate characteristics a character is born with.
Backgrounds are characteristics that are accumulated over a period of time
in a character's history.
Backgrounds tend to be of a more social nature than Gifts and Flaws.
</para>

<formalpara>
<title>Purpose of predefined Backgrounds</title>
<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>To work as hooks and inspiration for describing a character's history.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>To be a guide on what aspects of a character's history to focus on that could be relevant in a game session.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>By assosiating each Background with a value (but not making it a Gauge - that is, not have it increase during play) we will have a way of grading Backgrounds (to indicate its severity/power) and also to compare characters and NPCs with the same or relating Backgrounds.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</formalpara>

<screen>
Example Background values:
   | Severity/Power
---|---------------
 1 | Minor
 2 | 
 3 | Moderate
 4 | 
 5 | Extreme
</screen>

</sect1>
