<sect1>
	<title>Magic</title>

	<para>
	<quote>To the magician the magical act, that of causing a transformation
	in a thing or things with or without any physical contact, is accomplished by an
	imaginative act accompanied by the will that the wanted change will occur.
	The magical act and imaginative act becomes one and the same.
	The magician knows with certainty that for the change to occur he must will
	it to happen and firmly believe it will happen.
	Here it may be noted that magic and religion are akin:
	both require belief that a miracle will occur.</quote>
	</para>

	<para>
	Willpower should be an integral part of doing magic. Only the really
	headstrong and will-full should be able to change reality by will alone.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	When power is drawn from external sources (internal being the mage
	himself), other attributes than willpower should be considered.
	More spiritual attributes might be used - as in psyche, or maybe even
	aura as in gaining the "favour" of an entity able to bestow power on the
	mage.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	I'm thinking gathering the necessary energy should be tiring and hence
	increase fatigue.
	Controlling or conducting the energy should..
	Source uses WIL
	Conductor uses PSY/INT
	</para>

	<para>
	How magic works mechanicaly:
	</para>

	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>
	When the desired effect, source and conductor is decided, the mage starts
	to gather the energy (Source check). This should take time proportional
	to the energy gathered. A mage should have a potential that will limit
	the amount of energy he is able to gather at any one time. If this potential
	is exceeded, the mage could (read: should) be in trouble. 
	The mage is using his own body/soul/whatnot as a temporary storage
	for the gathered energy. Exceeding the potential may result in overload!
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	When the desired amount of energy is gathered, the mage will then channel
	this energy into the desired effect (Conductor check). If this check fails,
	magic is astray and weird things might happen.
	This should take time proportional to the intricacy of the desired effect.
	The more complex the effect, the more time is required.
	The process may be speed up at the cost of an increased Conductor TD.
		</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	
	<para>
	Gather, contain, conduct. Your typical Fireball<superscript>TM</superscript> spell.
	</para>

	<para>
	Gather, conduct while continued gathering (continuous flow of energy).
	This would be more subtle effects over a prolonged period of time (seconds, minutes, days, even years).
	</para>
	
	<para>
	Aim conduction, gather and conduct (continuous flow of energy).
	</para>
	
	<para>
	Magical potential: Could use a mage's Magical Source skill.
	Gathered energy = Magical Source tr lvl [+ Talent (WIL?)]
	</para>
	
	<sect2>
		<title>Magic and the Planes</title>
		<para>How do the Planes affect the various ways of performing Magic?
		</para>
		
		<para>Elemental magic should be enhanced when performed on the Elemental Planes.
		For instance, Fire magic should be enhanced on the Plane of Fire, Earth magic should be enhanced on the Plane of Earth, etc.
		</para>
		
		<para>Similarilty, specific conductors of elemental magic should be diminished or even cancelled when used on unrelated or opposed Elemental Planes.
		Fire cancelled on the Plane of Water, Air on the Plane of Earth, etc.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	
</sect1>
