<sect1><title>Distributing DNet</title>
<para>
This game is available free of charge from the several on-line archives.
This game may be freely reproduced and distributed electronically or in hardcopy,
provided the following conditions are met:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Leave all copyright, distribution, attribution, and DragonNet Team information
intact. Permission expressly granted for conversion to other formats.
Translation of this game to other languages must include the following
disclaimer on the title page, both in English and in the target language:
</para>

<para>
<quote>
<emphasis>
This document is a user translation of the DragonNet RPG.
It is not endorsed or otherwise acknowledged by the DragonNet Team.
</emphasis>
</quote>
</para>

<para>
You can contact the DragonNet Team for official approval of your translation.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
For-profit distribution of printed versions of the guide is forbidden, unless
permitted in writing. However, you may print out copies and recoup the cost of
printing and distribution by charging a nominal fee.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Any for-profit non-paper distribution (such as shareware vendor diskettes,
CD-Rom collections, etc.) must be approved by the DragonNet Team (the time- and
usage-based access fees of on-line services, bulletin boards, and network
access providers are specifically exempted).
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
You may not charge a for-profit fee specifically for this game, only for a
collection containing the guide, with the exceptions of nominal copying charges
and on-line usage fees as exempted above).
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Qualitative modifications of this game must include the following disclaimer on
the title page:
</para>

<para>
<quote>
<emphasis>
This document is a user contributed work designed for use with or in lieu of
the DragonNet RPG. It is not endorsed or otherwise acknowledged by the
DragonNet Team.
</emphasis>
</quote>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
