<sect1><title>Terms and Concepts</title>
<para>
To play a DNet game, there are a few terms that must be known.
We've tried to keep terminology to a minimum, but it inevitably creeps in.
Where we have specific terms for RPG constructs, we have tried to make them as
intuitive as possible.
</para>

<sect2><title>Talent</title>
<para>
Talent (Tal) describes a character's natural ability in a particular area.
A character's Strength Talent is a measure of their ability to lift loads,
carry weight and deal damage in combat. Other systems refer to a characters
natural abilities as attributes or abilities. We use the term Talent.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Training</title>
<para>
Training (Tr) is the amount of learned experience a character has in a given
Skill or area. This includes formal and informal education, obtained at a
university or the school of hard knocks. A character gains training
through practice, study and use of Skills. Experience can be used to 
increase a characters Training Level (Tr Lvl) in a Skill.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Skill</title>
<para>
Skill (Sk) is the effectiveness of a character in a particular area. Skill
includes both the characters natural Talents and his Level of Training.
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Sk = Avg(Tals) + Tr Lvl
</literal>
</para>

<para>
DNet is a Skill based system, so most of a character's abilities will be
described as Skills.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Heaps</title>
<para>
Heaps are numeric values that start at 0 and go up. High Heap values are
bad and low Heap values are good.
</para>

<para>
Some Heaps used in DNet:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Encumbrance
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Fatigue
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
Injury
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Heaps work similarly to Task Difficulties (TDs), except that they are variable.
For example, when a character takes sufficient Injury, he makes a survival
check by rolling dice and comparing the result (modified by appropriate Talents
or Skills) to his Injury Heap.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
