<sect1><title>What is DragonNet?</title>
<sect2><title>DragonNet RPG</title>
<para>
DragonNet (DNet) is a Role Playing Game (RPG) developed by a group of
volunteers over the Internet. The game is donated to the gaming community as
described under copyright and license. We hope that you enjoy our game. We
encourage you to use it; to change parts that don't fit in your game worlds;
to create new monsters, spells and rules; and to share your creative efforts
with other gamers.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Why Another RPG?</title>
<para>
There are a lot of RPG systems out there. Almost everybody has their
favorites. Everybody has played AD&amp;D (tm). There are new games every year.
Why another one? Well, we weren't happy with the other games we've seen
for several reasons. We felt that if we could use what we've learned from
years of gaming experience, we could develop a system that corrected the
mistakes and imbalances of other games. We hope we've accomplished that. 
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title><emphasis>"First Kill all the Lawyers" - William Shakespeare
</emphasis></title>
<para>
As many of you know, TSR has recently cracked down on the distribution of
user created materials for use with their AD&amp;D (tm) game. The letter
posted to rec.games.frp.dnd written by a TSR lawyer to a sysadmin 
caused quite a stir. Was there a company that provided a game where 
users were encouraged to develop material for the game and use it 
freely? We couldn't find one so we decided to develop our own.
</para>

<para>
The intellectual property owned by some game company is not what makes
role-playing an enjoyable hobby. (We argue it is their intellectual
property that causes many of the problems!) We decided to develop our own
fantasy RPG that would meet the needs of the net.community. One that could
be enjoyed without fear of legal retaliation. 
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Open Systems Development Philosophy</title>
<para>
Unix is a popular computer operating system for two primary reasons. One:
it's free (usually), and Two it uses an open system architecture. Computer
operating systems and RPG's actually have a lot in common. They are simply
a set of logical rules combined with a syntax. This combination results in
a system where user defined modules interact. RPG mechanics are also a set
of rules and syntax for the purpose of role playing or story-telling. If
Unix can be successful as a free system with open system architecture,
DNet should be successful as a free open-system RPG.
</para>

<para>
You already know what free means, and it's nice not to have to shell out
$20.00 for the latest RPG game. Not to mention the continual drain on your
pocketbook for the latest supplement. So what does open-system
architecture mean? Well simply it means that you know all the information
that was used to design the system. You are free to tinker with the insides
of the system. You can change it. Improve it. Distribute it. Expand it.
Bend it. Fold it. Mutilate it. Staple and spindle it.
</para>

<para>
In fact we knew when we started this project we wouldn't have the time to
fully develop every aspect of a good RPG. We hope you will take the
opportunity to carve out a portion of reality. Study it carefully. Ponder
it as you read through our Designer's Notes. Write up your new material
and distribute it to the gaming world. That is after all why we started
DNet. We felt it would serve our own self interest. We want to see what you
can develop. 
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Design Philosophy</title>
<para>
If you want to design materials for use with DNet you have two options.
You can develop unnofficial material yourself. Or you can join
the DragonNet Team. Either way, you'll want to understand the design
philosophy we employed in creating the DNet game. 
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>The Quest for Realism</title>
<para>
Almost all of us started RPG's with one of the early RPG systems. It was
fun for a while, but as we progressed they lost some of their charm.
Perhaps our character had progressed to beyond the 10th level and game
balance was forever lost. Maybe we no longer felt we had enough options,
or it seemed stupid that our fighter could dive off a 100 foot cliff into
solid rock and pick himself off the ground with relatively minor injuries.
In any event, we decided we could improve the system. We started by
working within the systems framework. Soon we exhausted all the
possibilities. Many of the problems were fundamental flaws in the games
themselves unable to be easily fixed without causing major problems
somewhere else. Next we moved on to other systems. We tried RuneQuest(tm)
or RoleMaster(tm). Then we moved on to "third generation" games such as
Hero (tm) or G.U.R.P.S. (tm). Still we were unsatisfied. We questioned why.
These games were rich with detail. The realism we craved was there. Why
did they lack the charm of those first RPG sessions? 
</para>

<para>
The reason we believe is that realism is not the grail RPG designers
should seek. Adding realism for it's own sake takes away the wonder of the
game. The mechanics begin to bog down the flow of play. We lose the drama
inherent in the plot. The story becomes dull. The game unplayed. The true
alignment principle game designers should strive for is elegance. An RPG
can be realistic to the extent that it uses simple, fast moving mechanics.
Gritty realism is less important than plausibility. An RPG is much like a
novel. Many realistic games get bogged down in the mechanics. This is as
dangerous for a GM as concentrating on technique alone would be for a
writer. The RPG system is there to enhance the story. The story is not a
vehicle for the RPG system. 
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Simplicity vs. Complexity</title>
<para>
Within the context of an elegant game, simplicity is key. When game
mechanics are simple and can be handled quickly they contribute to an
enjoyable role playing session. When they are bulky, get in the way, or
require frequent die rolls or multiple table lookups we lose the sense of
action, the drama of the events happening in the game world. Complexity is
an enemy that must be guarded against. If we fail to be watchful it creeps
into our systems. It destabilizes game balance and slows the play. The
rules drive the game. This is not what a RPG should be. 
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Key Development Principles</title>
<formalpara><title>Simplicity</title>
<para>
DNet should be a very simple game to play.
All the numbers needed for play should be available on the player's character
sheet. Non-player-character (NPC) stats should easily fit on a A5 card.
Table lookups should be infrequent or non-existent, particularly during play.
Only a limited number of dice should be used (d10 and d6). Dice mechanics
should be similar, and there should be no more than 2 or 3 varieties.
Skill and Talent checks should occur in basically the same manner.
Simplicity should not however preclude the richness of systems enjoyed by
experienced players.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Intuitive</title>
<para>
DNet should be intuitive. Jargon and acronymns should be avoided.
High die rolls should be good, low rolls bad. Game abstractions should make
sense relative to the real world. This should not be confused with realism.
DNet is not a detailed, gritty, realistic system. Abstractions have a basis in
reality. As an example in AD&amp;D (tm), hit points are an abstraction that
includes luck, skill, endurance and physical health. When you lose hit points
in AD&amp;D (tm) you are not necessarily taking wounds.
This kind of abstraction should be avoided.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Flexible</title>
<para>
DNet as a licensed game will be available for all Game Masters (GMs) to tinker
with. This should be encouraged, even built into the system. Each section of
the game, Character Creation, Combat, Magic, etc. should have a set of basic
rules that are easy to play, understand and use. Each section should also have
a set of advanced rules that add flavor to the game. These advanced rules
should allow characters to move seamlessly between the systems. All advanced
rules would be strictly optional. GMs could pick and choose among the optional
rules they will use.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Expandable</title>
<para>
DNet is an Open-System design. As such, it should be easily expandable by the
user. The game design should be such that players and GMs can easily add
Species, Cultures, Careers, Skills, Spells, etc. without disturbing game
balance or violating the integrity of the system.
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Quality</title>
<para>
DNet should be a high quality product. Suitable for publication by any of the
major game publishing companies. It should include quality color artwork, be
well written and meticulously edited. It should be made available through
anonymous ftp as text, postscript, and through www as hypertext formats.
</para>
</formalpara>
</sect2>
</sect1>
