<sect1><title><emphasis>Advanced Movement (Optional)</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
The movement rules detailed below attempt to cover in a sensible manner most
game situations where movement plays a critical part. However, they might be
cumbersome in situations where movement is not critical and the GM is free to
use them when and as he wishes. It is only suggested that he employs the
standard movement speeds (Base, Walking, Running, Sprinting and Max).
</emphasis>
</para>

<sect2><title><emphasis>Movement Speeds</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
Movement speeds are divided in five broad categories: Base, Walking, Running,
Sprinting and Max.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
The Base movement speed is the reference from which the four others are
calculated. The speed of a character in a melee combat situation is also equal
to the Base speed (see Movement and Distances in Combat).
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
The Walking speed is equal to a good but sustainable walking pace, the Running
speed is a moderate jogging and the Sprinting speed is a hurried run. For
comparison purposes, olympic marathoneers runners move at a pace between
Running and Sprinting (~ 19 km/h) and the Max movement speed listed is
that of the olympic sprinters (100 meters in 10 seconds).
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
In order to simplify the rules, it is considered that all members of a Species
can sustain the speeds given in the table below, for a short period of time
(until their first movement check).
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<table frame="all"><title><emphasis>Movement Speeds</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="5" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colname="c2" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colname="c3" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colname="c5" colwidth="1*" />
<spanspec spanname="aspan" namest="c2" nameend="c3" align="center" />
<spanspec spanname="bspan" namest="c4" nameend="c5" align="center" />
<thead>
<row><entry morerows="1"></entry><entry spanname="aspan"><emphasis>Human</emphasis></entry><entry spanname="bspan"></entry></row>
<row>                            <entry><emphasis>km/hour</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>m/round</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>Other Species</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>Fatigue Rating</emphasis></entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry><emphasis>Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>3</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>5</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>In Species description</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(1)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Walking</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>6</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>10</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>2 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(1)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Running</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>12</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>20</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>4 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(3)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Sprinting*</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>24</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>40</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>8 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(7)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Max**</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>36</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>60</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>12 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(10)</emphasis></entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<emphasis>
*: 100 meters in 15 secs
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
**: 100 meters in 10 secs
</emphasis>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title><emphasis>Movement Checks</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
A character must do periodic movement checks to see if he can continue to
move at a given speed despite the accumulated Fatigue. The checks are
done using:
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<literal>
d10-d10* + Movement Skill &gt;= Movement TD + Fatigue
</literal>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
At the end of each movement period, the character's Fatigue Heap must be
increased by one plus his Encumbrance Penalty. The check is made after Fatigue
has been increased. The Skill that is used in the check depends on the speed
at which the character goes (see Movement Skills).
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
If the character's roll added to his Movement Skill is greater than his
accumulated Fatigue plus the Movement TD, then the character can continue
moving at the same speed. If not, then the character must slow down by his Base
speed (a human Running at 12 km/h would slow down by 3 km/h and would thus end
up at 9 km/h). A character can accelerate at any time, as long as he has been
successful in his last movement check.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Note that Fatigue is necessary for the movement rules, even if it is not used
in other parts of the rules. Using Fatigue with the movement rules gives
pretty realistic results.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
While the base TD is -5 up to the Sprinting speed, the frequency of the checks
changes with the movement rate.
</emphasis>
</para>

<example><title><emphasis>Fatigue Frequency Check</emphasis></title>
<screen>
<emphasis>
A character needs to check only once per hour when Walking but
must make a check every minute when Sprinting.
</emphasis>
</screen>
</example>

<para>
<emphasis>
The faster the character goes, the faster he gets Fatigued.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<table frame="all"><title><emphasis>Activity vs Check Frequency</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="4" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colnum="4" colname="c4" align="center" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry><emphasis>Activity Level</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>Check Frequency</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>Movement Speed</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>Fatigue Rating</emphasis></entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry><emphasis>Light</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>1 hour</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>Base, Walking</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(1)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry></entry><entry><emphasis>30 minutes</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>3 * base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(2)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Moderate</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>15 minutes</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>Running</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(3)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry></entry><entry><emphasis>8 minutes</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>5 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(4)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry></entry><entry><emphasis>4 minutes</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>6 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(5)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry></entry><entry><emphasis>2 minutes</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>7 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(6)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Heavy</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>1 minute (10 rounds)</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>Sprinting</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(7)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Strenuous</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>5 rounds (30 seconds)</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>9 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(8)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry></entry><entry><emphasis>3 rounds</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>10 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(9)</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry></entry><entry><emphasis>1 round</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>11 * Base or more</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>(10)</emphasis></entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Basically, the frequency of the checks double each time the movement speed
increases by the Base speed.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
A character can always start to Walk, Run or Sprint without a check, as long
as he doesn't try to go over the standard Sprinting speed (see Heavy Sprinting)
or does not suffer from heavy Fatigue. If the GM judges that a character is too
tired to move, he can require a movement check before the character starts to
move (no Fatigue is added to the Fatigue Heap before making this check). If the
check passes, then the character moves normally. If the check fails, then the
GM can either impose a maximum speed for the character or require that the
character rests before starting to move. In the later case, the character can
attempt to move as soon as his Fatigue Heap has been reduced by one point or
more.
</emphasis>
</para>

<example><title><emphasis>Marathon Runner</emphasis></title>
<screen>
<emphasis>
A human runner wants to finish a marathon in about 2 hour and 10 minutes. To
cover the 42 km in 130 minutes, he needs to go at about 19 km/h, which is
approximately equal to 6 times the Base speed of 3 km/h. He will thus have to
make a movement check every 4 minutes. (Note: running a marathon in 2h10min is
a world class performance.)

Our marathon runner has an Endurance Skill of 30.
After 4 minutes of running, his Fatigue Heap is increased by one and he has to
make a first movement check:

d10-d10* + Endurance &gt;= -5 + Fatigue
d10-d10* + 30        &gt;= -5 + 1

It is quite obvious that he has virtually no chance of failing this check.
In fact, he is almost certain of being successful in the first 25 checks
(unless he rolls a fumble). This well trained runner can thus run at 19 km/h
for 100 minutes (25 checks * 4 minutes/check) without any major problem.
It only starts getting difficult for him in the last 30 minutes, when he has to
give his last energies to maintain the same rhythm.
</emphasis>
</screen>
</example>

<para>
<emphasis>
If a similar situation occurs in a game, it is strongly suggested that the
GM does not require the players to roll for checks that are always successful
unless the character fumbles. The players should not have to roll as long as
their Skill is 10 points higher than the TD.
</emphasis>
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
<emphasis>
For our marathon runner, this means that we need to roll only the last seven
check.

The first of these check is:

d10-d10* + 30 &gt;= -5 + 26

while the seventh is:

d10-d10* + 30 &gt;= -5 + 32

If he makes these seven movement checks successfully, he will have completed
the marathon in 2 hours and 10 minutes!
</emphasis>
</screen>
</informalexample>
</sect2>

<sect2><title><emphasis>Heavy Sprinting</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
The Sprinting speed given in the movement Speed table is the speed that all
members of a Species can sustain for a short period of time (1 minute). If
a characters wants to go faster than the standard Sprinting speed, he faces
a greater difficulty than just having to make more frequent checks. For each
increment of speed equal to the Base speed, 5 is added to the TD.
</emphasis>
</para>

<example><title><emphasis>Sprinting</emphasis></title>
<screen>
<emphasis>
Thus, to run 100 meters in 10 seconds, a character would need to go at 
60 meters/round, which means an increase of 20 of the TD.
In addition, the character needs to make a movement check every round.

The check that a human needs to make to run 100 meters in 10 seconds is:

d10-d10* + Sprinting &gt;= 15 + Fatigue
</emphasis>
</screen>
</example>

<para>
<emphasis>
When a character wants to move at a speed greater than the standard Sprinting
speed, he also needs to make an initial movement check. No fatigue is added
to the Fatigue Heap before making this check (Fatigue is always added at the
end of the movement period).
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
If a character tries to move faster than the Sprinting speed but fails his
check, the maximum speed that he can reach is obtained by substracting Fatigue
from his total roll and comparing the result with the movement TD in the table
below. The maximum speed that he can reach corresponds to the maximum movement
TD that is smaller than or equal to his adjusted roll.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
<emphasis>
If a sprinter rolls a total 6 on his movement check and has a Fatigue of 3,
then his adjusted roll is 3 and he can reach a maximum speed of 9 times the
Base speed (45 meters/round for a human).
</emphasis>
</screen>
</informalexample>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
The maximum speed that a character can reach is equal to 12 times the Base
speed. For a human, this speed is equal to 60 meters/round, which is equivalent
to running 100 meters in 10 seconds, a feat that only olympic athletes can
achieve. Of course, the GM is free to remove this limitation on maximum speed.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<table frame="all"><title><emphasis>Speed vs Movement TD</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" align="center" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry><emphasis>Speed</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>Movement TD</emphasis></entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry><emphasis>Sprinting or below</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>-5</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>9 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>0</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>10 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>5</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>11 * Base</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>10</emphasis></entry></row>
<row><entry><emphasis>Max</emphasis></entry><entry><emphasis>15</emphasis></entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</para>

<para>
<example><title><emphasis>Sprinting</emphasis></title>
<screen>
<emphasis>
An olympic athlete with a Sprinting Skill of 25 is on the starting line for the
100 meters race. As he is fully rested, his Fatigue is initially equal to 0.
Upon hearing the gun, he jumps from the starting blocks.

An initial movement check is made:

d10-d10* + Sprinting &gt;= Movement TD + Fatigue
d10-d10* + 25        &gt;= -5 + 20     + 0
-2       + 25        &gt;= 15
23                   &gt;= 15          -&gt; success

This initial movement check is successful and the character is thus moving at
60 meters per round. However, since his speed is equal to 12 times the Base
speed, he must make a check every round. He will thus have to make another
check after one round (6 seconds) of running. His Fatigue Heap is increased by
1 due to the first round of Sprinting and his second movement check is:

d10-d10* + Sprinting &gt;= Movement TD + Fatigue
d10-d10* + 25        &gt;= -5 + 20     + 1
3        + 25        &gt;= 16
28                   &gt;= 16          -&gt; success

This second check is also successful and the sprinter makes it to the finish
line in 10 seconds!
</emphasis>
</screen>
</example>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
