<sect1><title>Encumbrance</title>
<para>
The Load that each character can carry without ill effects varies with his
Strength and is given in the Strength table. When a character is loaded with
more weight than his Strength allows, his Fatigue rises faster than if he
was normally loaded.
</para>

<para>
The additional Fatigue that a character suffers when he is heavily loaded is
equal to the Encumbrance Penalty, which is calculated from the Load and Load
Step values of the Strength table. When the carried weight is lower than or
equal to the character's allowed Load, then the Encumbrance Penalty is equal
to 0. When the weight carried is greater than this Load, the Encumbrance
Penalty is increased by one for every increment of weight equal to Load Step
(or fraction of Load Step).
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Encumbrance Penalty = (Weight-Load) / Load Step (round up)
</literal>
</para>

<example><title>Encumbrance Penalty</title>
<screen>
A character with STR = 2 can normally carry 35 kg and has a Load Step of 3.5 kg.
If the character chooses to carry 40 kg, i.e. he carries 5 kg more than allowed,
he faces an Encumbrance Penalty of 2.

Encumbrance Penalty = (40 kg - 35 kg) / 3.5 kg
                    = 5 kg / 3.5 kg
                    = 1.43            
                    = 2 (rounded up)

Each time this character will increase his Fatigue Heap, he will increase it
by 3 (1 plus the Encumbrance Penalty). See the Fatigue rules for more details.
</screen>
</example>

<para>
The Encumbrance rules only takes into account the mass of items, not their
bulkiness. As always, a GM may state that the character suffers an additional
penalty on his Skill checks because he is loaded with large items.
For example, a GM has the right to impose a penalty of 10 on all Skill checks
to a character who is carrying a canoe, even if the character has the Strength
to do it. This is left to each GM, as we feel that such situations are not very
common and that threating them here would just add unnecessary complexity to
the rules.
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Optional: The GM can decide that the Encumbrance Penalty is also applied on
some or all Skills checks in addition to contributing to Fatigue;
he can also decide that Encumbrance only affects Skill checks if the Fatigue
rules are not used. When the Encumbrance Penalty is applied on a Skill check,
the TD is increased by the value of the Encumbrance Penalty.
</emphasis>
</para>

<example><title>Skill Check With Encumbrance Penalty</title>
<screen>
<emphasis>
If the character from the example above wants to jump over a 1.5 meters fence
while carrying 40 kg, the GM can decide to apply the Encumbrance Penalty on the
Skill check:

d10-d10* + Jumping Skill &gt;= TD + Fatigue + Encumbrance Penalty
</emphasis>
</screen>
</example>
</sect1>
