<sect1><title>Fatigue</title>
<sect2><title>Efforts</title>
<para>
Each time a character performs an action, he accumulates Fatigue, be it mental
or physical. This accumulated Fatigue makes it harder for him to perform
subsequent actions. At some point, he is too Fatigued to do anything correctly
and has to rest. (For simplicity, both mental and physical fatigue are
encompassed by the Fatigue Heap).
</para>

<para>
Some Skills will tire a character faster than others.
</para>

<example><title>Efforts</title>
<screen>
Reading is less draining that moving 10 kg rocks to build a wall.
Thus, the person moving rocks will get tired much faster than the person who
is reading.
</screen>
</example>

<para>
To take this into account, each character has a Fatigue Heap, which is
initially at 0 when he is fully rested and which increases as the character
performs various activities. The more exacting these activities are, the
faster the Fatigue Heap increases.
</para>

<example><title>Fatigue Rating</title>
<screen>
Taking a second look at our above example, we could qualify reading as a light
Effort, while moving rocks would be a moderate Effort. The character moving
rocks would thus have to increase is Fatigue every 15 minutes, while the one
reading would only increase it every hour (see the table below).
</screen>
</example>

<para>
The Fatigue Heap is always increased by 1 plus the Encumbrance Penalty (see
the Encumbrance rules) each time it is augmented, no matter which
activity is performed. The frequency at which the Fatigue Heap is increased
depends on the effort required by the Skill or activity. In the case of
Skills, one or more Fatigue Ratings will be associated with various uses of
the Skill, which makes it easy to find the Fatigue increment frequency. For
movement, this frequency depends on the movement speed (see the movement rules).
As usual, the GM can always change the frequency at which Fatigue is increased.
</para>

<para>
While many Skills will have one or Fatigue Ratings associated with them, the
GM will often have to determine how wearing a Task is. In that case, we
recommend that the GM describes the effort required in words and then
associates this effort with the appropriate frequency for increasing Fatigue.
</para>

<informalexample>
<screen>
For example, a Task that requires a moderate-heavy effort would require to
increase the Fatigue Heap every 4 minutes.
</screen>
</informalexample>

<table frame="all"><title>Fatigue Rating</title>
<tgroup cols="4" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="1*" />
<colspec colnum="4" colname="c4" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Effort</entry><entry>Recuperation</entry><entry>Frequency</entry><entry>Fatigue Rating</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Light</entry><entry>...</entry><entry>1 hour</entry><entry>(1)</entry></row>
<row><entry>...</entry><entry>...</entry><entry>30 minutes</entry><entry>(2)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Moderate</entry><entry>Rest</entry><entry>15 minutes</entry><entry>(3)</entry></row>
<row><entry>...</entry><entry>Sleep</entry><entry>8 minutes</entry><entry>(4)</entry></row>
<row><entry>...</entry><entry>...</entry><entry>4 minutes</entry><entry>(5)</entry></row>
<row><entry>...</entry><entry>...</entry><entry>2 minutes</entry><entry>(6)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Heavy</entry><entry>...</entry><entry>1 minute (10 rounds)</entry><entry>(7)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Strenuous</entry><entry>...</entry><entry>5 rounds (30 secs)</entry><entry>(8)</entry></row>
<row><entry>...</entry><entry>...</entry><entry>3 rounds</entry><entry>(9)</entry></row>
<row><entry>...</entry><entry>...</entry><entry>1 round</entry><entry>(10)</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<para>
Note: the Fatigue rules are optional for most Skill checks but is recommended
for the magic and movement rules. In the magic rules, Fatigue limits the
number of Spells that can be cast, while in the movement rules it limits the
distance that can be covered.
<!--
If you do not use Fatigue for magic or movement,
you will end up with an insanely heroic setting (where characters can sprint
for 100 km or cast 100 spells in a row...).
-->
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Recuperation</title>
<para>
A resting character recovers one Fatigue point every 15 minutes. A sleeping
character recovers one Fatigue point every 8 minutes (or two every 15
minutes). Samples activities that can be considered as resting are: talking,
eating, sitting, meditating, ... Of course, the character must not perform
another activity at the same time.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
