<sect1><title>Master Career List</title>
<sect2><title>Ancient careers</title>
<sect3><title>Acrobat/Actor</title>
<para>
Acrobats and Actors were important parts of Medieval life. The travelling
circus (as we still know it today) originated long before the Middle Ages and
was a great source of entertainment, morale and revenue for towns and cities.
</para>

<para>
As most people lacked formal education and could not read, actors were
important to portray various roles that told of topical and historical events.
Though not much training was available for these jobs, those who held the
positions were not highly regarded in social circles.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Acrobatics/Acting 50%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>50% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Apothecarist</title>
<para>
An Apothecarist was one trained and skilled in the arts of formal medicine.
Though not as highly regarded as a physician, these workers devoted their time
and studies to the arts of healing. Trained physicians were expensive and
usually only retained and hired by kings, nobles and the elite. Therefore the
Apothecarist served the common people.
</para>

<para>
Commonly a monk or priest held the position and most available remedies came
from the natural uses of plants, herbs and roots. It is believed that most of
these practical applications were first discovered by the Celts and Druids.
</para>

<para>
An Apothecarist who was a member of a religious order often charged a donation
to his sect for his services. A layman who served in the same occupation could
charge whatever fees he or she wanted.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Botany 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Chemistry 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Herbalism 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Medicine 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% Free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Architect</title>
<para>
Architects built structures, towns and buildings. Not only did they possess the
knowledge to construct these things but they also had the skill to plan entire
cities. Architects were highly in demand and were paid high wages for their
services. As war spread across Europe during the Medieval Ages it was important
for a king to have an architect who could build strong, reliable and defensible
towns, buildings and castles.
</para>

<para>
Much of the Gothic architecture that stands today throughout Europe was built
during the Medieval Ages. Churches, castles, cathedrals and theaters were often
not only functional buildings, but statements of a king's wealth and power.
</para>

<para>
The Medieval Architect had to have skill in math and a creative mind. In many
cases is a city or castle was conquered by an enemy the architect would be put
to death. Having his buildings mastered by an enemy was the ultimate sign of
failure.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Drawing/Painting 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Engineering 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Stonemason 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Wood Working 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Armorer</title>
<para>
The Medieval Armorer held a very important position in the workforce. Not only
were his skills highly required by nobles and monarchs, but the commoners
enlisted his services during times of war as well.
</para>

<para>
The Armorer was usually a blacksmith as well but as war became a more frequent
event, many blacksmiths could afford to relinquish their skills of crafting
metalworks and strictly pursue the field of making armor. It paid dearly for
them as a suit of armor could cost the modern equivalent of $60,000.00 -
$90,000.00 or even more! Armor had to be uniquely crafted to fit its wearer and
as such it was considered a specialty line of work.
</para>

<para>
Most Armorers were members of the Middle Class and were often very wealthy
indeed.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Armorer 40%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Blacksmithing 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Leather Working 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Metallurgy 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Artist</title>
<para>
Artists were common during the Medieval Ages but only the best were conscripted
by kings, nobles and the elite to produce portraits. Preserving the images and
likeness of a person and his family served as a contribution to history and
future generations.
</para>

<para>
The Medieval Artist often went from town to town seeking business but once an
artist had a royal or noble commission and if his work was worthy, his career
was made. Perhaps the two most famous Medieval artists are Michaelangelo and
Leonardo da Vinci.
</para>

<para>
The mediums used by most Medieval Artists were varied. Most preferred oil-based
paints that were manufactured by mixing different agents into berry-dye.
Watercolors were also popular and enamel painting was in its early stages.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Drawing/Painting 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Sculpture/Carving 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>25% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Astrologer</title>
<para>
The study of the stars and planets was not a new science in the Medieval Ages
but it was regarded as being mystical. The Astrologer did not only use the
heavens as a reference but he or she also studied the earth, the weather cycles
and the seasonal patterns. It was believed that through these things a better
understanding could be gained for agriculture and other social successes.
</para>

<para>
Many astrologers posed various and opposing theories. Some claimed the earth
revolved around the sun, others claimed that it was the moon that revolved
around the earth. In fact, part of Christopher Columbus's journey to the
Americas in 1492 was partially to dispel a theory that the earth was flat.
</para>

<para>
Sometimes Astrologers were accused of practicing witchcraft as their studies
took them into unorthodox techniques and discoveries. The Druids were thought
to be the first to seek a true understanding of celestial bodies and experts
argue that the mystical Stonehenge is nothing more than a lunar calendar.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Ancient History 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Astronomy 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Local History 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Theology 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Weather Sense 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Baker</title>
<para>
The Baker was a common occupation but not as easy as some may think. In the
Medieval Ages there was a period when bakers began cheating the public at such
a rate that public outcry reached the ears of several kings. As bread was a
daily staple of Medieval life, the bakers knew that they could charge a lot of
money for minimal portions of their products. As such, kings levied laws
against bakers stating that they were to lower their pricesand keep honest.
In fact the common term "A Baker's Dozen" (meaning 13 instead of 12) came from
this time period. Any baker caught selling less than an even dozen was strictly
and harshly punished. As a result bakers began adding one extra loaf to be
certain their count would be correct or even over the amount decreed by law.
</para>

<para>
Good bakers were often invited and employed by the rich and elite as personal
cooks and chefs inside the safety of castles. Their duties included the
preparation of dinners and large feasts. There were exceptional bakers of all
classes.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Cooking 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Drinking 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Eating 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Haggling 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>30% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Barrister</title>
<para>
The Barrister was a professional lawyer. Legal arbitration was popular during
the Medieval Ages as people challenged claims to land, inherited holdings and
even common law. Different provincial territories were usually subjected to the
laws of the local lord who governed them. As such, litigation could easily
arise between the residents of two neighboring communities.
</para>

<para>
Often a local priest would be consulted to act as a Barrister but as times
progressed people realized that there were high wages to be earned for the
skilled and professional lawyer. After much litigation and arbitration arose
and as disputes became difficult to settle under the umbrella of conflicting
laws, a new system for order was instituted. A policy called "The King's Law"
became the sole source of legal behavior permissable throughout sovereign
lands. Each successive king could change any law he deemed fit but the people
were bound legally to adhere to it.
</para>

<para>
Barristers became well respected during the Medieval Ages and helped to write
and form many of the laws that we still practice today.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Law 40%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Bookbinder</title>
<para>
An occupation that was extremely important but receives very little credit is
the position of the Medieval Bookbinder. This skill was very important as
diaries, journals and manifests were being written during the time period.
News of discoveries, law, science, medicine, technology and industry were
recorded on paper and were then bound together in the format of a book by
professional binders.
</para>

<para>
As there were no machines for printing, each journal and book was meticulously
and painstakingly handwritten. The Bookbinder had to be careful when setting
the pages together to not tear, damage or destroy any portion of the
manuscript.
</para>

<para>
Many of these books still survive today in Churches and museums and serve as a
testament to the excellent work performed.
</para>

<para>
Bookbinders usually joined a guild where they learned the trade as an
apprentice.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Drawing/Painting 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 45%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>30% among Knowledge Skills</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Bowyer</title>
<para>
The Bowyer (also called a Bower or Fletcher), crafted and manufactured bows,
arrows, crossbows and bolts. The effectiveness of the standard bow in combat
was first recognized by the Barbarian armies of Eastern Europe around 1070 AD.
But it was not until October 4, 1189 that Archers and bowmen established
themselves at the Battle of Acre and proved the quality of the bow as a weapon.
</para>

<para>
From that point forward, the bow became a standard weapon. It was easy to craft
by those who knew the skill and was readily affordable to most people. Bowyers
worked with a variety of woods and tools. A well crafted bow had durability and
even balance. The skill was much in demand and remained a premier trade until
the 1600s.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Archery 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Bowyer 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Cross Bows 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Wood Working 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Brewer</title>
<para>
The Brewer made and fermented beers and ales. The process was completed through
combining and aging hops, barley, wheat, malt and grain. The beverages were
served as a staple of daily life and were consumed in pubs, alehouses, taverns,
castles and homes.
</para>

<para>
During sieges and combat, historical documentation often tells of 'barrels of
beer' being delivered to the troops. The beverage was so important to the
fighting men that a document even states that at the Battle Of Sempach on July
9, 1386, the fighting actually stopped in mid-battle so that wagoneers could
deliver kegs and barrels of beer to each respective military.
</para>

<para>
Brewers were permitted their own enterprise during the Medieval Ages but since
their product was so highly in demand it often fell to heavy taxes and levies
being placed upon its sale and at times, even its consumption.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Agriculture 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Brewing 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Dringking 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Haggling 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>40% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Bricklayer</title>
<para>
Bricklaying was common labor and though it did not require vast knowledge or
skill, those who showed agility at the work were often subjected to an
abundance of employment and decent pay.
</para>

<para>
Often was the time when a king or noble would receive news that an approaching
enemy army was marching toward his towns and castle. The agile Bricklayers were
then conscripted to build retaining walls and obstacles and even reinforce the
towns and communities that were threatened.
</para>

<para>
Not only did war contribute to the benefit of the Bricklayer, but events such
as fires and floods were often left to his protection. By rapidly constructing
walls and ducts, it was possible to divert fires and floods and thus spare an
entire city, castle or town.
</para>

<para>
Bricklayers though quite common throughout the Medieval Ages were highly
respected members of their social orders.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Drawing/Painting 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Engineering 40%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Stonemason 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Candlemaker</title>
<para>
The Candlemaker was a specialist with many talents. Though making candles was
(and still is) a relatively easy project, the craftsman also had to have a
knowledge of the bees that provided him with the substance to complete his
work.
</para>

<para>
Once the wax was made a wick constructed of cord or twine was soaked in an
oil-based soltuion, inserted into the center of the wax mold and then the
candle was either pressed or shaped by hand. Candles provided illumination and
were also necessary for church ceremonies.
</para>

<para>
It's believed to have been in the 11th Century when a Candlemaker by the name
of Graham Overhill invented a candle with twelve markings (lines) on it.
When lit at the top of the hour, the candle would burn from line to line at the
rate of one hour each. Thus Overhill's candle served as a clock as well.
</para>

<para>

Though specific skills were required, candlemaking was an easy craft and it was
never known to provide more than a modest income.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Sculpture/Carving 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Theology 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Zoology 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>35% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Carpenter</title>
<para>
Carpenters were highly skilled and considered to be elite tradesmen. To become
a Carpenter it was usually necessary to join a guild as an apprentice and learn
the craft.
</para>

<para>
Most items used during daily life in the Medieval Ages were produced and
manufactured by carpenters. Homes, wagons, tables, furniture, tools and
utensils were all the creations of these gifted workers.
</para>

<para>
Knowledge of math, woodworking and the use of tools was required. Though many
of the implements used were basic in comparison to those employed today, it can
be argued that some fine examples of work were produced during the Middle Ages.
</para>

<para>
Kings and nobles often sought out the finest carpenters and kept them retained
on their staffs as specialists. Furnishing castles and estates was not only
done for decorative purposes but also to demonstrate prestige and status to
visitors. Thus a master carpenter was always in demand and could stand to earn
high wages.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Carpentry 40%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Wood Working 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>25% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Cartographer</title>
<para>
Cartographers (or map-makers) held a very important position in service to a
king or noble. As information of terrain and the oceans became known and
available, it was the job of the Cartographer to draw a detailed map of a given
area. These maps had to be accurate for many reasons. For example if a king
ordered his army to march into an enemy land he needed to know of land and
topographical features such as mountains, forests and rivers. Not only did
these places serve as barriers that were difficult for his troops to traverse,
but they also provided his enemies with advantageous places to launch ambushes
and attacks. As such, detailed maps were highly sought after. Also, it was
important to note new lands dicovered on ocean voyages as it gave kings the
opportunity to subjugate new areas.
</para>

<para>
Cartography was also important to distinguish boundries of neighboring kingdoms
or fifedoms. Sometimes devious nobles had false maps drawn and they allowed
them to 'slip' into the hands of their enemies.
</para>

<para>
The cartographer had to be an artist as well, versed in reading and writing and
skilled with math and geography.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Cartography 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Geography 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Direction Sense 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Navigation 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Clothier</title>
<para>
Clothing was not an available commodity to the lower classes and peasantry
until the 12th Century. In contrast, as the elite and members of the nobility
could afford the lavish prices of clothing, those who made garments (called
Clothiers) were sought after for their skills.
</para>

<para>
Being a Clothier meant having a knowledge of various materials and how to
assemble them into fine pieces of wear. The clothing of the time had to be
durable, fashionable and decorative as even during the Medieval Ages, clothing
was more of a status symbol.
</para>

<para>
The Clothier had to be experienced with mathematics, design and skill for
assembly. If serving the nobility a handsome profit could be made. But when
fabrics became available to all classes, the Clothier earned a modest living.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Math 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Drawing/Painting 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Leather Working 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>35% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Cook</title>
<para>
It seems that during any time period the position of a Cook was usually
thankless and difficult. The Medieval Ages were no exception. As methods for
preserving food were not invented to any degree of effectiveness, Cooks often
used salt to preserve meats and fish. The winter weather provided snow and ice
to act as refrigeration but often preparing a meal was no easy task.
</para>

<para>
Spices and extracts that we take for granted today were highly expensive during
the Medieval Ages. Trade routes were still being discovered and items such as
saffrin, ginger and cinnamon came from the Far East. Thus, a delicious meal was
usually enjoyed by only those who could afford the components to make one.
</para>

<para>
Feasts were held to commemorate holidays and important political events. These
meals were served to hundreds of guests and sometimes thousands.
</para>

<para>
It was necessary for the Cook to impress the friends of his lord or master.
There are many instances on record, such as the event in the year 1302 when Sir
Henry Campbell, master of Lamberth Castle, had his Cook imprisoned for serving
a meal that was considered poor.
</para>

<para>
Though a wide variety of foods were available in the Medieval Ages, a good Cook
only earned an average living with fair wages.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Agriculture 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Cooking 25%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Haggling 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>40% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Diplomat</title>
<para>
Those fortunate enough to possess the skills to become political Diplomats were
often on the road to nobility and positions of title. The Medieval Diplomat
served as a royal messenger and ambassador to the king, queen or noble he
served. Diplomats would often be sent on missions to speak on behalf of the
monarchy to rival kings or ruling houses. The Diplomat would negotiate
political deals such as peace treaties, hostage or prisoner releases and
matters of trade, commerce and economics.
</para>

<para>
The Diplomat needed to be firm, loyal and dedicated to the master he served and
it was also required that he have excellent speaking skills, the knowledge of
reading and writing and a shrewd manner.
</para>

<para>
If a Diplomat successfully delegated a trade or commerce pact he was often
entitled to a percentage of the revenue this new deal generated. Therefore
Diplomats were often wealthy people. However the astute Diplomat knew how to
negotiate deals that not only favored both rival parties but also was to his
own benefit. The Diplomat could reap financial reward from both factions if he
curtailed the deals to fit his own interests.
</para>

<para>
Often Diplomats were the educated members of the Upper Class and elite
societies. They often held titles such as Count, Duke or Baron and normally
retired with great wealth and prestige.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 25%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Haggling 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Law 25%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 35%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>5% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Dyer</title>
<para>
Dyers used their skills to mix different components to form inks, dyes and
colorful stains that could add tint and hue to clothing, furniture, fabrics,
materials and artwork. Not only did they possess the ability to decorate
fashionable wear but they also provided scribes and artists with the materials
necessary for them to complete their work.
</para>

<para>
The Dyer had a multi-faceted job. Not only was the making of the various dyes
difficult and tedious work but often it was dangerous too. Different berries
and plants used to create the pigments often contained a degree of poison that
was lethal if handled, inhaled or accidentally ingested. Though the Dyer put
his or her life in jeopardy by working, the wages earned were quite meager and
below average.
</para>

<para>
Most women held the positions of Dyers and though some were elevated to
strictly work for the elite and nobility, most worked in small towns and
communities.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Botany 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Agriculture 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Herbalism 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Chemistry 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>30% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Engineer</title>
<para>
Engineers are evident throughout history beginning in ancient Egypt and
reaching a position of prominent status in ancient Rome. These skilled
tradesmen were essential to the successful expansion of any political kingdom.
Not only were cities and towns improved by their skills but warfare and daily
life saw better odds with the meaningful contributions of Engineers.
</para>

<para>
Difficult tasks such as building expansion bridges, reinforcing the
subterranian foundations of castle walls, building powerful siege engines for
use in battle and even irrigation and aquaducts were a few of the jobs
Engineers were called upon to perform.
</para>

<para>
In the Medieval Ages without the refined tools, knowledge and materials
available today, the above tasks were considered monumental feats of
achievement. Not only did such things improve the morale and efficiency of a
kingdom but it also stood to prevent disease in the areas of plumbing and
rubbish removal and even served to be more productive in irrigating crops and
providing water.
</para>

<para>
Engineers did most of their work by 'trial and error' and though kings and
nobles recognized and acknowledged the wide margin for potential failure, such
could end the life or career of a skilled Engineer. Though many feats were
undertaken for the very first time, such enterprises were costly and put a
strain on the financial reserves of a kingdom. However, Engineers were highly
respected and were usually employed by the most rich and powerful kings and
queens of Medieval society.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Engineering 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Drawing/Painting 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Physics 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Read/Write 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Engraver</title>
<para>
An Engraver was a specialist who was often called upon to etch messages and
designs into swords, shields, armor and metal plaques. An artist in his own
right, he worked with a variety of custom tools to produce his trade.
</para>

<para>
Though the artform has been modified by the advances in technology of today,
the Medieval Engraver practiced his craft in a most time consuming and
painstaking way. If the results of his work were unattractive or undesirable,
the customer would often not pay or even had legal grounds to sue the Engraver
for ruining a piece of private property. As such the Engraver had to produce
quality work.
</para>

<para>
Despite being a specialty, Engravers were quite common throughout the Medieval
Ages. The wages earned were generally modest but being conscripted or hired by
a noble or monarch for a custom project could find him the recipient of high
pay.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Drawing/Painting 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Heraldry 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Metallurgy 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Sculpturing/Carving 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Wood Working 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Farmer</title>
<para>
Farming was the most popular occupation of the Medieval Ages as it was an
essential element to survival. A local lord or master would grant portions of
his land to commoners and serfs and in exchange the people would till,
cultivate and maintain the property to produce crops. What was grown was
eventually sold at local markets at which the peasants were allowed to keep a
share. Most revenue went to the local lord however through taxes and levies.
</para>

<para>
In the society of the Middle Ages, a man's status was based on how much land
and livestock he owned. As both of these elements were critical for revenue, a
private farmer who owned his own land could become quite rich.
</para>

<para>
Crops were varied and depended greatly on how fertile the plot of farmed land
was.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Agriculture 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Botany 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Foraging 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Cooking 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>35% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Fisherman</title>
<para>
The Fisherman was much like the farmer in that he provided food as a commodity
and thus sustained the survival of towns and villages. Usually a professional
fisherman worked on a boat owned by a noble or local lord. The work would begin
at sunrise as the boats would depart to cast lines and nets into oceans, lakes,
rivers and causeways. Fish tended to fetch a higher price in the market because
of the rapid rate at which they deteriorated and spoiled.
</para>

<para>
A fisherman who had his own boat was not necessarily in a position to
capitalize on free enterprise. Though he was entitled to operate legally by
himself, most waterways were the legal right and claim of kings and nobles.
Therefore limits were imposed on the private fisherman as to how much bounty he
could haul out of the waters. Even then, higher taxes were assessed on him in
the markets to ensure that the regent or local master got his due share.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Fishing 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Cooking 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Weather Sense 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Seamanship 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>30% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Forester</title>
<para>
The Forester usually held a position equal to a sheriff or local law enforcer.
He was responsible for patrolling the woodlands on a lord or noble's property.
His duties included negotiating deals for the sale of lumber and timber and to
stop poachers from illegally killing animals in the forest.
</para>

<para>
Many times wanted criminals would flee their arrest warrants and seek the
safety of hiding in a forest. When this would occur it was the duty of the
Forester to oragnize roving gangs of armed men to flush out the criminal and
capture him.
</para>

<para>
Often Foresters held titles of prominence in their local communities and also
acted as barristers and arbitrators. Their pay was usually above average and
they could stand to make a decent and profitable living.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Law 25%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Haggling 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Hunting 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Tracking 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Riding (land) 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% among Combat Skills</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Fortune-teller</title>
<para>
Fortune-tellers were often looked upon with disapproval from the ruling classes
but their services were highly in demand. The Medieval Ages were full of
superstition and very real belief in supernatural forces and powers. Most
things that could not be explained by science or technology was thought to be
the direct influences of these powers at work.
</para>

<para>
The common people were normally quite stressed economically and therefore they
viewed the Fortune-teller as a potential advantage to overcoming future
difficulties. If their future could be revealed they believed they could take
steps to improve upon it.
</para>

<para>
Most Fortune-tellers were common rogues and tricksters who used a variety of
simple illusions to create dramatic effects. Though they possessed no real
skill at all for devining the future, they would be careful to use basic events
and information to project a scenario that was generic enough to fit into
anyone's situation. Once embellished with mild promises of prosperity it seemed
a true magical experience had taken place. Often though the Fortune-teller's
success was based on how much the person getting the reading wanted to believe.
</para>

<para>
Some Fortune-tellers did use lunar and celestial patterns to predict probable
and basic outcomes in terms of weather. These natural signs could foretell
famine or draught or even bad storms. If a Fortune-teller had success in
predicting these events, his or her credibility was greatly enhanced.
</para>

<para>
A few kings and monarchs did enlist the services of seers and Fortune-tellers
to predict the future of their kingdoms and even the outcome of battles. Though
there was a given ratio of success and failure based on mathematical
probability, the fortune-tellers with luck and agility managed to earn
positions of respect and wealth in some courts.
</para>

<para>
However, most were treated as witches or dark practitioners. And in some cases
when their foretold events did not ring true, they were hunted down and killed.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Astronomy 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Begging 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Oration 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Truthtell 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>30% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Furrier</title>
<para>
The Furrier worked with the pelts and hides from animals. not only did he use
the fur to make clothing but also rugs, blankets and even inner linings for
armor.
</para>

<para>
If a Furrier operated with wisdom he could become quite profitable in his
trade. Different regions produced different animals and with careful and legal
trapping he could import and export furs to different regions that were
considered exotic and hard to get.
</para>

<para>
Hides and pelts were treated in a variety of ways, usually by coating the
underside with an oil-based substance to protect it from deterioration. Then it
was usually hung in the sunlight or a dry area so the liquid could dry and act
as a sealant. The fur was treated with different powders and a liquid
containing lye. This preserved the fur for wuite a long time.
</para>

<para>
Though some furriers achieved great wealth the common occupation paid very
modestly.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Botany 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Chemistry 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Hunting 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Leather Working 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Tracking 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Gardener</title>
<para>
The Medieval Gardener was considered a specialist at his trade. He was mainly
responsible for the upkeep and cosmetic appearance of castles and estates but
he was also called upon to build defensive ditches and barriers during times of
war.
</para>

<para>
Throughout Europe there are many forms of ivy that grow wild. These plants tend
to grow upward along stonefaces and as such, castles were prime for this
problem. Enemies could use the sturdy ivy to climb and grapple the walls to
gain access. Therefore it was important to have a Gardener who could cut down,
trim and destroy these potentially dangerous plants.
</para>

<para>
A knowledge of herbs, plants and flowers was essential. Most Gardeners served
some form of nobility or local lord but even though a portion of their work was
critical to the safety and protection of a castle or estate, they were paid
meagerly.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Botany 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Herbalism 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Sculpure/Carving 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Philosophy 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>30% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Gravedigger</title>
<para>
Unfortunately the Gravedigger could stand to make a profitable living during
the Medieval Ages. As epidemics, disease and war were rampant the Gravedigger
was never short on business.
</para>

<para>
During the Black Plague it was recorded that a Gravedigger named Marshal de
Clare reaped such a profit that he was able to afford estates, manors, castles,
land and livestock. Marshal de Clare later became a local lord, hired a retinue
of knights and became a lesser ruling house in Southern England.
</para>

<para>
No special skills were required for the profession but it did call for a
careful handling of the tools.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Endurance 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Streetwise 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>75% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Herald</title>
<para>
A Herald was not an occupation that someone trained for, but rather a job that
was usually the appointment by a king or noble. Most often a domestic servant
in a castle would be elevated in rank by receiving this appointment from his
master.
</para>

<para>
The Herald (or Harker) would declare announcements on behalf of the king to the
public. Normally this was done on a given day when the public would assemble at
the base of a castle tower and the Herald would shout out the news and
proclamations or the Herald would do his job in the local townsquare. It was
the responsibility of the Herald to inform the public of what was going on.
(Note that many newspapers to this day are called "The Herald")
</para>

<para>
The only requirements one needed to perform this job successfully was a good
speaking voice, the ability to read and write and obedience to a local lord.
Two of the most famous men in the Medieval Ages who held the role of a Herald
or Harker are Geoffrey Chaucer (author of the Canterbury Tales) and Nigel Gray.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Heraldry 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 35%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Law 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Oration 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Streetwise 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Herbalist</title>
<para>
A Herbalist was usually a member of a religious order such as a monk or friar.
His main duties included the planting and maintaining of medicinal plants,
roots and herbs. Different from a Gardener in that he didn't maintain large
estates or actively participate in forming defensive ditches, the Herbalist
enveloped himself in the deep studies of medicine.
</para>

<para>
Many herbs have natural healing agents and as medicine was still in its early
stages, the Medieval Herbalist was a much respected person. Normally the church
would provide a plot or tract of land that was cultivated by either religious
personnel or by peasants who received minor wages. The Herbalist would then
plant and maintain his select crops in the area.
</para>

<para>
A lot of the plants needed to undergo treatments such as boiling, drying,
steeping or steaming to bring out their healing properties and some needed to
be combined with others to find the desired results. The Herbalist therefore
had an elaborate and involved study and needed the components of a laboratory
to do his work successfully.
</para>

<para>
Those who belonged to religious orders usually did not stand to make high wages
as they were bound by laws of poverty. However a layman who acted as his own
Herbalist could sell his healing knowledge and services for extremely high
prices.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Biology 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Botany 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Cooking 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Herbalism 40%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Medicine 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>5% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Hunter</title>
<para>
The professional Hunter of the Medieval Ages had many resources at hand with
which he could earn money. Hunting was a special skill and though most people
had the basic knowledge needed for survival, professionals often circulated
among the elite nobility.
</para>

<para>
Hunting was a popular sport during the Medieval Ages but also extremely
dangerous. Kings and lords would hire a professional Hunter to lead their
party. Often they would hunt for animals such as wildboar, wolves or even bear.
Naturally the more tame animals such as deer, rabbits and foxes were the
targets of the general populace but there are many stories from the Medieval
Ages of nobles being killed during the more dangerous hunts.
</para>

<para>
Not only did the Hunter serve as a guide and expert, but he also had a
knowledge of skinning, tanning and preparing the meats that were captured on
the hunt. Also, he even managed to use the bones of the captured animals to
make products such as dagger hilts and used the teeth for jewelry and other
exotic items. As a result, the Hunter not only made a profit from hiring out
his services, but also made additional money from his skills and resourceful
talents.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Archery 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Cooking 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Hunting 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Searching 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Tracking 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Zoology 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Innkeeper</title>
<para>
One of the most lucrative and profitable occupations was that of the Medieval
Innkeeper, but only if all conditions were prime and if certain circumstances
were maintained.
</para>

<para>
Anyone who could afford the structure and property could embrace the free
enterprise of having an Inn, however he or she was subject to heavy taxes and
levies by the local lords of the area.
</para>

<para>
Owning an Inn carried a lot of responsibility. Besides the bedrooms the Inn
also had other internal features such as a dining rooms and often a tavern or
alehouse. Usually the fare for a room included meals as well. The alehouse was
sometimes leased by a secondary business person and often a separate enterprise
from the Inn.
</para>

<para>
Cleaning, maintaining and providing quality goods and services were the primary
requirements of an Innkeeper. One also had to be good with mathematics and
money and even have the presence of mind to calculate bookings and the ordering
of supplies and inventory. Most times an Innkeeper hired a small staff of armed
security guards. It was not uncommon for a group of fighters to arrive at an
Inn shortly after their latest campaign. Rowdy and hoping to spend the spoils
of war, the atmosphere inside most Inns and alehouses could be bawdy and even
at times violent.
</para>

<para>
At the doorway to an Inn you could find at least one armed guard posted. There
was usually a minimal entry fee to pass through the door, just a courtesy to
help pay for any damages that may arise while inside. The guard at the door
would take a brass or copper coin from the entrant and bounce it on a wet piece
of wood. If the coin bounced once it was clear that the coin was genuine and
the person was allowed to enter. Many times people would forge their own coins
out of lead or cheaper metals and since Europe saw a wide variety of foreign
money, it was often difficult to prove the authenticity of a coin. The practice
of bouncing the coin off of a wet piece of wood is what eventually led to
modern day doormen at bars and pubs being called "Bouncers".
</para>

<para>
Many times nobles and elite personnel were exempt from paying any fees at an
Inn or hostel. Though this was resented by most Innkeepers, they did receive
fair protection in return. If the business was maintained properly, an
Innkeeper could earn high profits.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Haggling 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 25%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Law 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Streetwise 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Interpreter</title>
<para>
Interpreters earned excellent wages despite whom they worked for. There was a
scarcity of people versed in more than one language and as a result,
Interpreters were highly sought after by kings and monarchs. Not only did an
Interpreter serve to reveal information about captured foreign troops, but also
he could compose letters, laws and doctrines that helped with the subjugation
of foreign territories.
</para>

<para>
Also it was necessary throughout the Medieval Ages to hold meetings,
conversations and diplomatic gatherings with nobles and ruling members of many
foreign countries. Therefore the Interpreter held an elite position and was
often given rank, land and titles in exchange for his or her valuable services.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Law 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languagess 75%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Jester</title>
<para>
The Jester seldom had an easy job. Though some were professionals and made
their livings touring from kingdom to kingdom, most were forced into the
position as an act of humiliation.
</para>

<para>
King Henry V often enjoyed taking captured Knights of elite title and rank and
forcing them to play the fool before his entire court. If the Jester was
successful at entertaining his troops and guests, he would be hauled back to
the dungeons after his performance to live to do it again another day. If the
Jester did not provide gleeful entertainment he was often tortured or killed.
</para>

<para>
Jesters lived precariously and often their success depended solely on the mood
of their audience. They did not earn high wages but were often allowed a few
benefits and luxuries of life inside a castle.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Acting 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Bardic Influence 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Juggling 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Musical Instument 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Jeweler</title>
<para>
Jewelers held great positions of status within Medieval communities and towns.
As foreign wars took troops into exotic lands they often returned with precious
stones and minerals. Not knowing the value of them, it was up to the Jeweler to
determine their worth.
</para>

<para>
Diamonds, emeralds, rubies and sapphires were the most common stones found
during the Medieval Ages. Gold, silver and bronze were also held in high
regard. The Jeweler not only held the knowledge of assessing values on these
items but he was also skilled in setting the stones into rings, pendants,
medallions, bracelets and amulets. The Jeweler also knew how to set the items
into sword hilts and other placements that exhibited the status and wealth of
their holders.
</para>

<para>
Jewelers were respected but there were many who knew the advantages of being
less than honest. Stones with minimum value such as quartz, zarconia and even
fools gold were not easily distinguished by the untrained eye of the public.
Therefore it was common for a Jeweler to accept a valuable diamond with the
promise of setting it into a ring or pendant for its owner. Simply, he would
polish a quartz or zarconia of similar size and dupe the owner by giving him
the worthless item. The Jeweler could then sell the original and more valuable
stone and reap a quick and high profit.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Apprising 45%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Haggling 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Metallurgy 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Leatherworker</title>
<para>
Leatherworkers were common laborers but their skills were in high demand. The
crafting of swordbelts, clothing, saddles and even leather armor were necessary
items for Medieval life.
</para>

<para>
Though some preferred the protection and skill that guilds provided, many were
able to learn the basics of the trade on their own.
</para>

<para>

The tanning process was relatively simple and though most commoners knew how to
do this, the products they made on their own didn't have the durability of
those made by Leatherworkers.
</para>

<para>
In order to be preserved, leather had to be treated by a series of steps.
Tanning, hiding and even treating the material with oils and softeners were
necessary to make it last longer and worth the money charged.
</para>

<para>
Leatherworkers earned a modest and sometimes decent living depending on the
quality of their skills.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Appraising 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Armorer 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Leather Working 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>35% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Locksmith</title>
<para>
Locksmiths were integral parts of Medieval society. Though most homes held
little more than an internal wooden slide lock on the insides, Locksmiths
became important with the developments and security of castles.
</para>

<para>
Their talents were in the beginning stages but an intricate lock that resisted
the efforts of picking or tampering was soon highly valued. Criminals and the
residents of dungeons often escaped rather easily when not secured with locks
or shackles. To maintain security Locksmiths were trained in guilds and the
secrets of their craft were kept highly guarded.
</para>

<para>
As such, Locksmiths were considered to possess the knowledge and skills of a
specialty organization and as a result earned high wages.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Drawing/painting 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Locksmithing 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Metallurgy 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Open locks 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Merchant</title>
<para>
Merchants needed to be wise in mathematics and negotiations. To trade goods and
services a Merchant needed to build a list of customers. And once established
he needed to maintain quality and timely service to keep them happy.
</para>

<para>
Most travelling merchants either sold grain, wheat, barley, oats, hops or other
commodities that could benefit a town or community. There was much competition
in this trade and a ruthless manner was often held between rival merchants.
Once the customer base was established it was important to maintain a decent
business ethic. Merchants often grew to be very wealthy and retired with
positions of title and rank.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Appraising 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Haggling 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Law 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Messenger</title>
<para>
Another popular phrase of today that stemmed from the Medieval Ages is "Don't
kill the messenger". The occupation of a Messenger was often dangerous but had
its merits.
</para>

<para>
Usually the Messenger was a lesser diplomat of sorts and spent his time in
service to a king or local lord. When news or a response to an inquiry needed
to be delivered to a rival ruling house it was the job of the Messenger to
undertake the duty.
</para>

<para>
When the message delivered was less than favorable the Messenger was often the
victim of the incurred wrath. Often times the Messenger would be inadvertently
blamed and either imprisoned or killed. This led to lesgislation and laws being
passed which eventually made the Messengers exempt from punishment due to the
news they delivered.
</para>

<para>
Messengers had to be skilled in topographical knowledge, horsemanship and had
to be articulate. They needed the skills of reading and writing and often
received high wages for their dangerous services.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Endurance 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Geography 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 35%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Riding (land) 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Miner</title>
<para>
Miners also held very dangerous jobs and often worked in extremely precarious
environments. The need to mine gold and silver was paramount as most kingdoms
increased their financial reserves by depending on these resources. Miners were
not overly skilled workers but it did require a bold resiliance to perform the
duties.
</para>

<para>

Apart from the collapsing of mines, deadly gasses and cave-ins, the Miner had
to endure several days at a time beneath ground. His wages were above the
standard pay in exchange for his difficult services but often Miners led modest
lives.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mining 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Metallurgy 40%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Endurance 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Minstrel</title>
<para>
Minstrels were musicians. Various instruments included the mandolin, fife,
flute, dulcimer, drums, violin and harpsichord. A great deal of skill and
training was required to become a professional musician and those lucky enough
to have proficiency on an instrument often found themselves entertaining kings
and nobles for high wages.
</para>

<para>
Minstrels often would record the deeds of heroic knights and go from tavern to
tavern playing these odes of homage. Not only did it make for an interesting
song, but it gave the knight publicity and established a degree of respect and
staus for him. Throughout the Medieval Ages, Bards became the popular employees
of any knight or common man who wanted their deeds enshrined in a public song.
The deeds were embellished of course but it was a wonderful way to spread the
fame of a knight from kingdom to kingdom. The talented Minstrels and Bards
frequently charged high prices for these services.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Bardic Influence 25%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Musical Instrument 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Streetwise 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>25% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Moneylender</title>
<para>
Banking was still in its developmental stages during the Medieval Ages but
there was always work to be found for a professional Moneylender. As kings
needed to increase their private funds to hire armies and finance campaigns,
they often sought the services of such an individual.
</para>

<para>
The Moneylender was able to set his own rules and since he was offering his
personal finances, he was often exempt from taxes and levies. His money was
often referred to as his "interest" being that it was the primary element of
his business. When lending money he would make his profit by charging a
percentage of the sum he was lending, to be paid back with the total owed.
Therefore if he lent 100 gold pieces to someone, he could charge 25% on his
"interest" and he would eventually receive 125 gold pieces back. His rates of
"interest" could vary and if a debtor could not repay the loan, the Moneylender
was entitled to seize land, livestock and holdings equal to what was owed.
</para>

<para>
The term "interest" still survives today and is commonplace with banks and
financial institutions. The Moneylender often made a lavish living.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Haggling 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Streetwise 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>30% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Navigator</title>
<para>
The Navigator usually worked closely with a Cartographer. His sole job was
steering vessels on a safe and even path to new destinations. Mainly they kept
their bearings and charted their courses by using reference points in the skies
by means of planets or stars. As they held steady positions in relation to the
earth, it was often easy for a trained Navigator to practice his trade.
</para>

<para>
Navigators also worked on the ground, guiding armies, troops, diplomats and
messengers through various features of terrain. Their services were highly
regarded and as a result they were well paid.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Direction Sense 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Navigation 40%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Riding (land) 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Seamanship 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Painter</title>
<para>
Though it is commonly believed that most Medieval towns and cities were quite
drab, this is a misconception. Communities were often highly decorated with
wreaths and color. The professional Painter was regarded as a tradesman who
could bring new residents to a community and also keep morale high by providing
an attractive place to live.
</para>

<para>
Festivals and tournaments saw great need for the Painter as his services were
in demand to produce lively environments. Though some skill was required it was
basically a trade that did not demand any formal training. Painters earned
modest wages but when conscripted by the service of kings or nobles, could make
a hefty profit.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Drawing/Painting 45%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>55% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Peddler</title>
<para>
The Peddler was a common merchant and often went from town to town selling
whatever goods he had to offer. The items could be anything from novelty items
to candles or even tourist-styled souveniers.
</para>

<para>
Usually the Peddler was an enterprising business person but often stood to make
meager earnings as their profits were subjected to high taxation by the lords
and nobles of the communities they did business within.
</para>

<para>
One seldom found a rich Peddler and often it was a means of basic survival.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Appraising 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Haggling 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Riding (land) 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>25% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Physician</title>
<para>
Physicians were very highly regarded and respected. Though their positions were
deemed prominent it took about a full century before their work was completely
accepted.
</para>

<para>
More skilled than an Apothecarist or Herbalist, the Physician was capable of
prescribing new medicines and performing types of surgery. These services were
often limited and dependant on the heavy purses of the rich and elite and as
such, many a commoner and peasant died simply because they could not afford the
services.
</para>

<para>
The Physician saw much opposition to his career during the 13th Century. Many
of his practices such as bleeding, lancing and surgical techniques were deemed
to be against the teachings and doctrines of Church Law. Therefore anyone wise
enough to know they needed the professional services of a Physician knew also
that they could risk punishment or excommunication by the Church.
</para>

<para>
During the 14th Century though the Church gradually began to accept the
merciful work of Physicians and they became wealthy and earned elaborate
lifestyles.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Biology 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Chemistry 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Herbalism 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Medicine 40%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Playwright</title>
<para>
Playwrights were necessary for many reasons. Good ones were difficult to find
and those who enjoyed success at this trade were continually hired by kings and
monarchs on a regular basis.
</para>

<para>
As most people could not read or write during the Medieval Ages, it was
important to act out history or crucial events in the form of a play. This
preserved history and gave the common people an understanding of how things
were gained and achieved.
</para>

<para>
The Playwright wrote his texts in the format of scripts and then hired Acrobats
and Actors to fill the roles. Often these performances would take place in
townsquares or anywhere in which a public audience could assemble. Many
Playwrights attempted controversial issues as the subject matter for their
plays and were subsequently arrested, imprisoned or executed. The wise
Playwright hovered around topics that were favorable by kings and law and
enjoyed great success and high wages.
</para>

<para>
Though at the end of the Medieval Ages, William Shakespeare (born 1564) was the
most popular Playwright of the time period.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Ancient History 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 50%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Local History 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Politician</title>
<para>
Medieval Politicians served in many different capacities. Whereas a local lord
ruled the lands of his fifedom, the local people were often allowed to elect
their own sheriffs, mayors and delegates to handle matters on smaller levels.
All matters of grave importance though were left to the decisions of
arbitrators, barristers and of course the local lord himself.
</para>

<para>
A Sheriff was a minor political post that carried great weight and authority.
Often answerable to the local lord his duties included the enforcement of law
throughout the local communities.
</para>

<para>
The Mayor was the voice of the people. Any concerns of the commoners were put
forth to the Major and either he could resolve the matters personally or seek
the counsel of a barrister or his local lord.
</para>

<para>
Delegates operated between the Sheriff and Mayor and often were directly in
contact with the people. When concerns or issues were raised the Delegates
would call meetings between the Sheriff and Mayor and attempt to resolve the
matters. The entire system was subject to the law of the local lord but many
times these lesser legislative bodies were effective in their duties.
</para>

<para>
Wages varied but usually Politicans had above average livings.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Law 25%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Oration 25%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Potter</title>
<para>
Potters were crafters of earthenworks and dealt mainly in clay molds,
porcelains and early forms of ceramics. Basically they produced pots for
cooking and storage and at times sculpted icons and statues to order.
</para>

<para>
Potters were usually members of guilds and worked closely with molds, tools and
heating kilns. Their craft was well respected and though their products were
much in demand on a daily basis, their wages were usually average.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Pottery 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Sculpuring/Carving 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>40% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Rat Catcher</title>
<para>
Though the very name of this position seems like a menial occupation, Rat
Catchers were very highly regarded in Medieval society and in fact, their work
was rather respected.
</para>

<para>
Rats, mice and vermin were often the cause of epidemics and disease. Therefore
a crafty and skillful Rat Catcher could earn stunning wages in ridding a city
or town of its pest problems. Often the work did take the professional Rat
Catcher into undesirable places and he did risk his own health and safety by
coming into contact with diseased and often rabid rodents.
</para>

<para>
However when he was successful at his trade he managed to gain local confidence
and increase his personal revenue. The Black Plague which killed over one-third
of Europe's population was mainly spread by the infected fleas that were
carried by rodents. Rat Catchers employed cats and means of trapping to bring
the problem under control and end one of the greatest and most damaging
epidemics to ever spread across an entire continent.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Animal Training 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Survival 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Streetwise 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>40% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Sailor</title>
<para>
Sailors often led lonely and hard lives and it was a most difficult occupation
during the Medieval Ages. It required a firm will and dedication as vessels
would often set sail for months or even a year at a time.
</para>

<para>
During voyages Sailors each had specific duties equal to the level of their
station. Overseeing the operation of a vessel at sea was difficult enough but
Sailors were constantly at work from sunrise to sunset. This served to keep the
Sailor busy and keep him from growing bored and discontented by the long hours
at sea.
</para>

<para>
Before the official formations of Navies, Sailors mainly sailed on ships owned
by kings, nobles and monarchs. Their pay was based on their rank. A common
Sailor earned very little while a First Mate or Boatswain earned much more
substantial wages.
</para>

<para>
Sailors needed training in the handling of the vessel, their duties at sea and
even ocean combat. The Sailor did not come into his full respect until the
advent of the Crusades when he became an important and key figure. Sailors
ferried troops, supplies, horses and foodstores from secured ports, through
hostile waters and resupplied the armies. Sailors were often a unique breed and
their main goal was to eventually reach Officer and receive command of their
own vessel.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Oration 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Seamanship 45%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Swimming 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Tactics 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>20% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Scribe</title>
<para>
To become a Scribe required skills in reading, writing and comprehension.
Scribes not only wrote volumes of works on the Medieval Ages but were also
often asked to research laws and other matters for kings and nobles.
</para>

<para>
The Scribe was often a historian, poet and philosopher. His acquired knowledge
was advantageous at the workings of social interaction and his skills provided
a written overview of the time period.
</para>

<para>
Scribes usually were of nobility in that the education needed to attain the
post was not affordable or available to peasant and common classes. Most
Scribes came from religious abbeys where the skills were learned within the
vast libraries of the church.
</para>

<para>
Their wages were usually standard and average, however the Scribe was entitled
to all the benefits and luxuries of castle life.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Ancient History 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 45%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Law 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Local History 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Teaching 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>10% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Servant</title>
<para>
There were advantages and disadvantages of being a domestic Servant. Though the
work was often tedious, menial and hard it was worthwhile if you were in
service to a kind lord or master. However, the difficult work when coupled with
a rude or abusive employer often led to harship throughout a Servant's life.
</para>

<para>
Usually Servants were conscripted if they possessed talents and abilities that
were useful inside a castle. Such things as cooking, baking, sewing, dying,
weaving or performing music could attract the attentions of a local lord. If
these conditions were met and the service was satisfactory, the Servant enjoyed
the mild benefit and protection of working within a castle.
</para>

<para>
Sometimes victorious knights would take their prisoners back to their homelands
and endenture them as Servants. This could be most embarrassing if the capture
person was an enemy knight. But while waiting to be ransomed or in order to
work off his debt, the enemy knight had no other choice but to lower himself to
the dutiful position of a Servant.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Cooking 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Etiquette 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>50% among Artistic and Craft Skills</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>35% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Shipwright</title>
<para>
The Shipwright (or Shipwane) was a skilled specialist who built and designed
boats and vessels. The most prominent and effective design came out of the Dark
Ages with the Viking Longboat. Modifications to that ship led to more
successful and safe sea journeys.
</para>

<para>
Having great knowledge of mathematics, design and science, the Shipwright was a
master craftsman. Often earning high wages and a lavish living, their services
were often demanded by kings and monarchs.
</para>

<para>
Their craft was in demand throughout the entirety of the Medieval Ages and
Shipwrights gained more respect in England when their designed vessels defeated
the Spanish Armada, a flotilla deemed unable of conquer.
</para>

<para>
Guilds usually provided the training but once a person achieved the status of a
Shipwright his future was guaranteed to be profitable.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Drawing/Paiting 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Engineering 40%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Physics 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Shoemaker</title>
<para>
Shoemakers (or cobblers) were often common laborers who designed and made
footwear. Anything from shoes fashioned from burlap, hide or leather to
elaborate and fancy boots made from reptile skins. Their work was regarded as
necessary but as the materials they worked with fetched high prices, not all
were able to afford them.
</para>

<para>
Shoemakers eventually curtailed their businesses to suit the needs of most
people and designed lesser pieces of footwear from cloth and even wood. Though
they appealed to the mass populace and even though their product was necessary,
Shoemakers often earned only average wages.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Apprising 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Drawing/Painting 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Haggling 5%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Leather Working 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Math 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>35% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Spy</title>
<para>
It was a wise king or monarch that kept informed of what was going on in rival
and neighboring communities and towns. Therefore it became necessary to hire
Spies to secretly find out what was afoot.
</para>

<para>
Contrary to popular belief, most Spies were women. It was generally accepted
that women could move in certain social circles more easily than men and using
their inherent charm, could naturally coax more information out of trusted
employees of rival houses.
</para>

<para>
These Spies were often trained with the uses of various skills such as reading,
writing and often speaking more than one language. They were also trained
assassins and took oaths that obligated them to take their own lives rather
than risk being caught by an enemy.
</para>

<para>
Spies were usually paid high wages and were given the luxuries of castle life.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Languages 40%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Streetwise 25%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Truthtell 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Stone Carver</title>
<para>
Stone Carvers were important in Medieval society. Their work consisted of a
broad range of talents from etching tombstones to carving tools and statues.
</para>

<para>
Members of this profession usually acquired their skills through joining a
guild. The guild also included masons and sometimes bricklayers, but normally
Stone Carvers were in a grouping of their own.
</para>

<para>
Most of their work took great durations of time to perform and it was often
necessary to retain a Stone Carver for many months. The crafty ones knew how to
further extend each project and though they produced quality work, they could
thus earn more money.
</para>

<para>
Their wages were usually higher than average and a Stone Carver could earn a
decent living.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Engineering 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Read/Write 10%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Stonemason 30%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>40% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Storyteller</title>
<para>
Storytelling was an integral part of Medieval life. As most people lacked the
ability to read and write, history, legends and folklore were passed along from
generation to generation through skilled Storytellers.
</para>

<para>
No special abilities were acquired to hold this position except for a decent
memory. However, the more industrious Storytellers also knew how to read so
that they could widen their collection of stories. Sadly, a great number of
Storytellers often embellished facts and added untrue elements to make their
stories more exciting and incredible. While this provided entertainment for
their audiences, historical facts often became distorted.
</para>

<para>
On average, Storytellers did not usually earn wages for their services unless
they were hired to perform at social gatherings. A few though did manage to
earn modest livings at the craft by entertaining kings and monarchs.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Ancient History 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Bardic Influence 15%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Languages 35%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Local History 20%</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>15% free</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Modern careers</title>
<para>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
