<sect1><title>Basic Premises</title>
<sect2><title>Combat Styles</title>
<para>
There is more to combat than just swinging a weapon; most of the reflexes that
make a good fighter have more to do with the way he uses his weapon than with
the particular weapon used. The Skills your character has to learn to be a
proficient fighter are thus named Combat Styles. The primary style for a
fighter with military training would probably be "One-Handed Weapons &amp;
Shield".
A northern barbarian wielding a claymore would most often use the "Two-Handed
Weapon" style. A magic oriented character would probably opt for a low cost
style such as "Staves", giving him basic combat abilities while letting him
focus most of his efforts on magic lore.
</para>

<para>
As your character gains experience, he can advance in one or more Combat
Style. Since Combat Styles are used for both attack and defense, improving
them makes you both harder to hit and better at hitting your opponents.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>The Combat Round</title>
<para>
As in many RPG systems, combat in DNet is resolved by dividing its duration
into rounds. During a round, each character can perform one action:
attacking an opponent, casting a spell, reloading a bow, etc. Each combat round
represents six seconds of action, giving ten rounds per minute.
</para>

<para>
During a combat round, each protagonist will get to accomplish one action,
without consideration for who acts first or last. Each attack/defense
confrontation is in fact an exchange of blows and the damage inflicted by the
protagonists upon each other is the summation of the effects of each
individual blow. It is therefore perfectly possible for two combatants to
finish off each other in the same round, giving a situation similar to the
final combat scene in the movie "Excalibur".
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Combat Round Sequence</title>
<para>
Most gamers hate it when the mechanics of combat system take more time than
the actions and tactical decisions of the characters. In other words, the
mechanics should not slow down the combat flow and bring down the climactic
tension. The combat round sequence outlined here and described more fully
later in the text will generally be most effective one for smooth combat
resolution.
</para>

<para>
The combat round begins with the declaration phase, during which each player
announces the actions of his character(s) and the GM states the actions of the
NPCs. The order of the declaration can be arbitrary or determined by rolling
for initiative. In both cases, it is advantageous to declare last, since you
can decide the actions of your character in regard of what others have
announced.
</para>

<para>
After all actions have been declared, the resolution phase begins.
No particular order is required, as all actions are considered to be
simultaneous and every character is assured that he will have a chance to
attempt its planned actions. For attacks, resolution is divided in two
steps: the attacker first attempts to hit the defender in a contest of
Skills; if he is succesful, Damage is calculated using the procedure outline
above.
</para>

<para>
At the end of each combat round, after all actions have been resolved,
characters that have been wounded during the round must check to see if they
remain conscious and alive.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Impact, Damage and Injury</title>
<para>
When you hit an opponent with a weapon, you generally intend to cause him some
physical damage. The DNet system uses a specific procedure with its
associated terminology to calculate this damage; the basics of the damage
calculation procedure are exposed here, so that you can better understand
the rest of the system. The complete procedure will be described in detail
later in the combat chapter.
</para>

<para>
Every physical attack is said to cause an Impact.
</para>

<para>
<example><title>Impact, Damage And Injury</title>
<screen>
A hit with bastard sword made by an average human causes 2d6+5 points of Impact.
If the target is wearing armor, part of the attack's Impact is absorbed by the
armor, while the remaining part, if any, constitutes the true physical Damage,
which is added to the target's Injury Heap.
If the target suffers too much Injury, i.e. more than what is Body allows,
he will pass out and eventually die.
</screen>
</example>
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
