<sect1><title>Combat Sequence</title>
<para>
This section explains in detail how combat is resolved in the DNet
system. To this end, a game situation leading to combat is developped as the
rules are presented.
</para>

<para>
Combat is broken down into rounds. Each round is considered to last 6
seconds. All actions that occur within a round are independent of each other
and are considered to take place at the same time.  Thus it is always possible
for two combatants to strike each other down in the same round.
</para>

<para>
Within a combat round, attacks and defenses are viewed as a passe d'armes, not
as individual strokes.
</para>

<example><title>Combat</title>
<screen>
Game situation: Neila and Jalik have been cautiously exploring the ruins
  of a temple of Hekari, an almost forgotten deity of darkness and disease,
  in the hope of lifting a curse that as been plaguing a pixie community
  for centuries. As they are about to despair, their efforts are rewarded
  by a hollow sound from a flagstone reveals a hidden passage. After
  doublechecking their torches and pushing the stone safely aside, they
  engage in the the shadows of a stairway.

The characteristics and appropriate skills and equipment of the two characters
are given here for reference purposes.

Neila (Bob's character)
Mental Talents:   AUR: 0; INT: 1; PER: 0;  PSY: 1; WIL: 2
Physical Talents: AGI: 2; BOD: 2; DEX: -2; FIT: 1; STR: 3
Combat Styles:
                          Tals + Tr = Skill
  One Handed W. &amp; Shield:   0  + 8  = 8      Attack: 8  Defense: 8+2+4 = 14
  Dodge:                    2  + 7  = 9      Defense: 9+4 = 13
Equipment:
  War Hammer (Impact = 2d6+4)
  Kite (defense bonus = 4)
  Soft leather bezainted armor (Resistance = 6)

Jalik (Roger's character)
Mental Talents:   AUR: 1; INT: 1; PER: 2; PSY: 0; WIL: 0
Physical Talents: AGI: 3; BOD: 1; DEX: 2; FIT: 0; STR: 0
Combat Styles:
                Ta + Tr = Skill
  Dual Weapons: 3  + 6  = 9      Attack: 9+2 = 11  Defense: 9-1 = 8
  Dodge:        3  + 5  = 8
Equipment:
  2 small swords (Impact = 2d6+2)
  a 2 meters wooden pole
  Quilt armor (Resistance = 3)
</screen>
</example>

<sect2><title>Declaration</title>
<para>
At the beginning of every combat round, the GM must ask every player to declare
the actions of his character for the round. The GM must also state the actions
of all NPCs and monsters during that phase. Once stated, these actions cannot
be changed, unless the GM feels that there has been a misunderstanding; in that
case, every player should be allowed to redeclare the actions of his character.
</para>

<para>
The declaration order does not really matter as long as the actions of all
protagonists are stated. A fixed order, such as going around the table will
generally speed game play.
</para>

<para>
Note that a character can attack multiple targets only if he is in close range
(0 to 1 meters) of both targets at declaration time.
</para>

<para>
<example><title>Declaration</title>
<screen>
Game situation: Jalik and Neila reach the bottom of the stairs about 5 meters 
  below the ground level.
  GM: In the torchlight, you can see that the floor is littered with
    bones.
  Roger: "[Whisper] Cover me." I slowly crouch to inspect the bones.
  GM: They look like humanoid bones, generally human sized.
  Roger: I inspect the walls, looking for holes or any trace of a mechanism.
  GM: You spend 5 minutes doing as careful an inspection you can
    without stepping on the floor. The walls are plain and smooth. You don't
    see any obvious crevasse.
  Roger: I slowly pass the wooden pole along the floor and the walls.
  GM: (rolling a few dice to make good impression) Nothing happens.
  Bob: "[Whisper] It looks ok?"
  Roger: "[Whisper] Yes... I go first, you follow me 4 steps behind."
    I advance in the passage, tell me when I notice anything different.
  GM: After 4 meters, the floor is clear of bones. The transition
    is gradual.
  Roger: I continue.
  Bob: I still follow about 2 meters behind.
  GM: You walk two more steps and hear a concert of clicking sounds
    as the bone quickly move along the floor to reassemble into three distinct
    shapes. Two of the shapes are near Neila, while the third is behind 
    Jalik's back. What do you do?
  Bob: "[Loud] Watch your back!". Neila attacks the nearest shape and will 
    dodge the two others if necessary.
  Roger: Jalik drops his pole and takes out his two swords. He will also
    attack the nearest shape.
  GM: Jalik's attack won't happen until next round, but they won't
    be able to attack this round either. Neila, you realize that you can 
    bash at the nearest one without worrying about dodging the other.
</screen>
</example>
</para>

<sect3><title><emphasis>Initiative (Optional)</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
Some role players find that basing the declaration order on the Talents of
their characters allow for more strategy during combat. A declaration method
which allow the characters with the best Perception to react to the actions
of others is presented here.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>Determining initiative:</emphasis>
</para>

<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para><emphasis>Roll 1d10</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Add Perception (you may get negative results)</emphasis></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
<emphasis>
Actions are then declared starting with the lowest initiative roll to the
highest. This gives a chance to characters with the highest Perception to
adjust their actions to those of others.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
All players should roll for initiative and the GM should also roll it for NPCs
and monsters. In large combats, the GM may wish to roll initiative for groups
of monsters or even for all monsters at the same time.
</emphasis>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title><emphasis>Alternate Initiative (Optional)</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
Another method to determen initiativ is to base the characters reactions on the
speed of their weapon and their Agility Talent. The more agile characters will
act faster than those less agile.
</emphasis>
</para>

<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para><emphasis>Roll d3 (d6 if surprised)</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Add Weapon Speed (WS)</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Subtract Agility</emphasis></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>
<emphasis>
Also with this mechanism actions are resolved starting with the lowest
initiative roll to the highest.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
The result is the Time Unit (TU) in which you start to act w/o penalties.
After the initital initiativ roll, simply add your WS each time you want to
make an attack and sum the numbers.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
One TU is roughly equal to 1 second.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
<literal>
Next TU you can act w/o penalties = Current TU + WS
</literal>
</emphasis>
</para>

<sect4><title><emphasis>Initiativ Modifiers (Optional)</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
You can choose to act earlier with a penalty of -5 per TU to early,
or you can increase your chance of success by delaying up to 5 TUs and
gain a +2 bonus for each TU.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
<literal>
Max Bonus = +10
</literal>
</emphasis>
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Action resolution</title>
<para>
Once all actions have been declared, they are resolved using standard Skill
checks. The order of the resolution does not matter (Unless you use the optional
alternate inititiv mechanism) since all actions within a round are considered
to be simultaneous. Again, resolving the actions in a fixed order will speed up
the game and simplify combat.
</para>

<para>
While there are no strict limits to the actions that can be attempted during
combat, we will focus here on the actions that are directly related to the
resolution of combat.
</para>

<sect3><title>Targeting</title>
<para>
The determination of an attack outcome is achieved using the targeting
equation:
</para>

<para>
<literal>
d10-d10* + SA [+ Sk mods] &gt;= d10-d10* [+ TD mods] + SD [+ Sk mods]
</literal>
</para>

<para>
If the left hand side is greater than or equal to the right hand side, then 
the attacker scores a hit and should proceed to determine Damage.
</para>

<para>
While this expression may seem complex, it summarizes a very simple process:
</para>

<para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>Both the attacker and the defender roll d10-d10*, as in a Skill check.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The attacker adds his Attack Skill (SA) to his roll, while the defender adds his Defence Skill (SD) to his roll.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>They also add any situation combat modifiers that the GM judge necessary to their respective rolls.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>If the attacker's total is greater than or equal to the defender's total, then the attacker is successful in his attack and should now roll for Damage.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>

<para>
The targeting roll can be modified by situation combat modifiers. These
situation combat modifiers are chosen by the GM and are broken into two
categories:
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Task Difficulty Modifiers (TD mods): modifiers that affect the difficulty of the combat Task.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Skill Modifiers (Sk mods): modifiers that affect the Skill of the combatants.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<table frame="all"><title>Task Difficulty Modifiers</title>
<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Condition</entry><entry>Modifier</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Target Semi-prone</entry><entry>-1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Target Prone</entry><entry>-2</entry></row>
<row><entry>Target Partly Immobile</entry><entry>-4</entry></row>
<row><entry>Target Immobile</entry><entry>-8</entry></row>
<row><entry>Target Invisible</entry><entry>+5 (Varies)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Target out of range</entry><entry>+1 / 10% beyond weapon's range</entry></row>
<row><entry>Target Size</entry><entry>(SR Attacker - SR Target)</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<para>
<table frame="all"><title>Skill Modifiers</title>
<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Condition</entry><entry>Modifier</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Semi-prone</entry><entry>-1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Prone</entry><entry>-2</entry></row>
<row><entry>Partly Immobile</entry><entry>-4</entry></row>
<row><entry>Immobile</entry><entry>-8</entry></row>
<row><entry>Poor Footing/Environment</entry><entry>-1 to ... (Left to GM discretion)</entry></row>
<row><entry>On higher ground than opponent</entry><entry>+1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Charging</entry><entry>+2 Attack, -2 Defense</entry></row>
<row><entry>Set to receive a charge</entry><entry>+2 Defense (assuming Attacker is charging)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Hasted</entry><entry>+2</entry></row>
<row><entry>Slowed</entry><entry>-2</entry></row>
<row><entry>Invisible</entry><entry>+5 (Varies)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Feinting</entry><entry>+5 (Optional)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Additional Action Attempted</entry><entry>-5 per additional action</entry></row>
<row><entry>Injury</entry><entry>-1/5 points or </entry></row>
<row><entry></entry><entry>-1/([BOD + 10] / 2) (Optional but more realistic)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Fatigue</entry><entry>-1/point (Optional)</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
The modifiers apply to both attack and defense skills, unless noted.
Modifiers that apply only to the attack skill are identified with
"+X Attack", while those applying only to defense are noted with "+X
Defense".
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Optional:
For NPCs, the GM may replace the defender roll by a constant value of 0 to
accelerate combat resolution:
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
<literal>
d10-d10* + SA [+ Sk mods] &gt;= 0 [+ TD mods] + SD [+ Sk mods]
</literal>
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
This increases the effects of a difference between the Skill levels of the
attacker and defender, i.e. the opponent with the Skill will win more often
than when both opponents roll for defense.
</emphasis>
</para>
   
<para>
<emphasis>
Of course, the GM can decide that neither PCs, nor NPCs roll for defense.
</emphasis>
</para>

<example><title>Action Resolution</title>
<screen>
Game situation:
  (first round) Neila swings her war hammer at the nearest skeleton.
  -&gt; Bob rolls 3 and adds Neila's attack skill of 8 for a total of 11.
  -&gt; The game master rolls -2, adds the skeleton guardian defense skill of
     8 and a skill modifier of -2 due to the fact that the guardian is still 
     taking shape, for a total of 4.
  Neila hits the skeleton and sends crushed bones flying. In the meantime,
  Jalik wields his two swords.

  (sixth round) Neila is still engaged with two Guardians; she has suffered
  a few hits but has nearly destroyed the first while dodging the other.
  Jalik has also hit is Guardian a few times, while taking only two hits.
  Neila's attack:
  -&gt; Bob rolls 23 (!), adds Neila's attack skill of 8 and substracts 5
     because of the multiple actions (attacking and dodging) for a total
     of 26.
  -&gt; Game master rolls -7 (!) and adds the skeleton defense skill (8) for
     a total of 1.
  ===&gt; Neila scores another precise hit on the first skeleton.
  1st skeleton's attack:
  -&gt; Game master's roll: -9 + 8 = -1
  -&gt; Bob's roll: -2 + 14 - 5 = 7
  ===&gt; Neila blocks the skeleton attempts.
  2nd skeleton's attack:
  -&gt; Game master's roll: 3 + 8 = 11
  -&gt; Bob's roll: -1 + 13 (dodge skill) - 5 = 8
  ===&gt; The skeleton hits Neila.
  Jalik's attack:
  -&gt; Roger's roll: 6 + 11 = 17
  -&gt; Game master's roll: -1 + 8 = 7
  ===&gt; Jalik successfully stabs at the skeleton.
  3rd skeleton's attack:
  -&gt; Game master's roll: 7 + 8 = 11
  -&gt; Roger's roll: 7 + 8  = 11
  ===&gt; The skeleton hits Jalik.

  Skeleton Guardians
  Physical Talents: BOD: 0; AGI: 0;  STR: 2
  Mental Talents:   INT: -8; PER: 0;
  Combat skills:
                          Skill
    Claw attacks:           8      Attack: 8  Defense: 8
    Dodge:                  5
  Special:
    Claw IMPACT: 2d6
    Natural Resistance: 5
    -2 to combat skills while taking shape.
    Fights until destroyed (no Unconsciousness checks)
</screen>
</example>

<sect4><title><emphasis>Realistic Combat (Optional)</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
You can split up both your attack and defence into smaller portions of your
total Skill, but you must use at least 1 Skill point to do an action.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Keep in mind that your SA and SD is in fact only one Skill. The numbers may not
be equal due to Attak- and Defence Modifiers (AM/DM).
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Thus, the amount of Skill you wish to use in an attack, a feint, a defence or
whatever is subtracted from both SA and SD.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
As long as either your SA or SD is greater than 0 you may continue to do
actions. If your SA is reduced to 0 you may not attack anymore.
And if your SD is reduced to 0 you may not defend anymore.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
The only situation where you may continue to defend even if your SD is 0, is
if your SA is greater than 0. Then you can use your remaining SA as SD.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Note: You can use SA as SD, but not the other way around.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
When both your SA and SD is equal to 0, you must wait in WS TUs before you can
do actions again. Or, if you are using the Optional Combat Modifiers, act
later/earlier with coresponding modifiers.
</emphasis>
</para>

<example><title><emphasis>Realistic Combat</emphasis></title>
<screen>
<emphasis>
Neila
Physical Talents: AGI: 2; BOD: 2; DEX: -2; FIT: 1; STR: 3
Mental Talents:   AUR: 0; INT: 1; PER: 0;  PSY: 1; WIL: 2

Combat Styles              Ta + Tr = SA/SD
  One Handed W. &amp; Shield   2  + 6  =  8/8
  Dodge                    2  + 7  =  0/9

Equipment     Type  IMPACT   SPD  DEF
  War Hammer   B     +5       1
  Kite Shield        -2           +4

Jalik
Physical Talents: AGI: 3; BOD: 1; DEX: 2; FIT: 0; STR: 0
Mental Talents:   AUR: 1; INT: 1; PER: 2; PSY: 0; WIL: 0

Combat Styles   Ta + Tr + AM + DM = SA/SD  SPD
  Dual Weapons: 3  + 6    +2   -1 = 11/8    1
  Dodge:        3  + 5     0    0 =  0/8

Equipment        Type  IMPACT   SPD
  2 Shortswords   S/T   0/0      1

Neila and Jalik decides to do some combat practice.
They start out beyond each others reach. Both rolling for initiative (d3).
Neila rolls a 2 + 1 (WS) = 3.
Jalik rolls a 1 + 1 (WS) = 2. Jalik has initiativ.

(In situations like this, its not nesessary to roll for initiative unless both
insist on attacking first.)

He decides to wait, focus his attention and observe Neila.

[In game terms: +2 bonus/TU to whatever action he decides later on.]

Now Neila has decided to see if the saying "Attack is the best form of defence"
holds true. But she knows Jalik is a skilled fighter and will try to feint for
a opening in his defence.

[In game terms: 2 points of her skill will go into an initial feint, 4 points
will go into the actual attack. The remaning 2 will be held back in case of a
counter attack from Jalik.]

She takes a few quick steps forward toward Jaliks right, holding her shield
between herself and Jalik, seeing Jalik drawing his defence to her feint, she
takes one long fast step to the right and lashes out at his left flank.

[In game terms:
Neila feints attack: d10-d10* + 2 + 5 (feint bonus)
                         -10  + 2 + 5 = -3 (a terrible feint)

Neila attacks: d10-d10* + 4
                     3  + 4 = 7
]

Jalik, seeing Nelias obvious feint, decides to play along, feinting a defence
where Neila expectes him to. Jalik decides for himself that due to Nelias
terrible feint, she will focus her energy mainly on the following attack.
With his left hand sword he decides to focus most of his skill to parry her
attack, and then counter with his right hand sword to lash out at her shield
flank, aiming for her (hopefully) exposed left leg.

[In game terms: 2 points of his skill will go into playing along with the feint,
6 points will go to the left hand defence and the remaining 5 points (3 from
his attack skill + 2 bonus points) will go to his last right hand attack.

Jalik feints defence: d10-d10* + 2 + 5 (feint bonus)
                            4  + 2 + 5 = 11 (a good feint)

11 &gt; -3 (Neilas feint attack) -&gt; Jaliks feint succeeded.

Jaliks left hand parry: d10-d10* + 6
                              9  + 6 = 15

15 &gt; 7 (Neilas attack) Jalik successfully parries Neilas attack.]

Neila, realising her failure as Jalik easily parries her attack and counters,
can do nothing but use her remaining skill to defend herself as best she can.

[In game terms:
Jaliks right hand attack: d10-d10* + 5
                                5  + 5 = 10

10 &gt; 6 (Neilas shield bonus + remaining defence).

Jalik hits Neilas left flank. Roll damage.]

Because this is only a practice session, Jalik holds back his attack enough for
Neila to just get a tiny scratch. She staggers backward to a defencive positon,
preparing herself for a new clash of arms.

In this situation, I guess we can say that attack was NOT the best defence. :)

This entire combat scene lasted only a few seconds. Both Jalik and Neila must
now regain consentraton, focus and whatever before they can act without
penalties. This is determened by their weapons SPD. They must wait in Time Units
equal to their SPD. This means they must both wait 1 Time Unit. Then they start
all over again.
</emphasis>
</screen>
</example>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Called Shots</title>
<para>
Targeting a specific body part is refered to as a Called Shot. While
targeting vital organs can increase the deadliness of an attack, those vital
organs are often small and thus more difficult to hit.
</para>

<para>
The table below gives Impact modifiers for some human body parts. These
modifiers are based on the probability of hitting a vital organ in the
targeted part. The effect of hitting non-vital organs is left to the game
master.
</para>

<para>
<informalexample>
<screen>
For example, a serious blow to the hand might cripple its victim in
addition of doing normal Impact.
</screen>
</informalexample>
</para>

<para>
Listing all such consequences is beyond the scope of these rules.
</para>

<table frame="all"><title>Impact Modifiers vs Body Parts</title>
<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec align="center" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Impact Modifier</entry><entry>Body Part</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>+10</entry><entry>Head</entry></row>
<row><entry>+15</entry><entry>Throat</entry></row>
<row><entry>+20</entry><entry>Eye/Heart</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<para>
When making a Called Shot, the targeting roll of the character is modified
by the Size Rating (SR) of the body part targeted. This SR can be determined
from the Size Rating table below. You can either estimate the average dimension
of the targeted part and look for a matching number in the size column, or just
scan the examples for a part of similar size.
</para>

<para>
Targeting equation for called shots:
</para>

<para>
<literal>
d10-d10* + SA &gt;= TD - SR
</literal>
</para>

<para>
Called Shots are generally applied to missile weapons. In melee combat
battling an opponent larger than you does not make him much easier to hit
since he also benefits from an extended reach.
</para>

<para>
Most values listed are for human body parts. You can convert to the species
being targeted very simply, by adding the Size Rating of the Species to the
Size Rating of the human body part.
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Body Part SR = Human body part SR + Species SR
</literal>
</para>

<example><title>Body Part Size Rating</title>
<screen>
SR of human arm  = -4
SR of weejon arm = SR of human arm + SR of Weejon
                 = -4 + -3
                 = -7
</screen>
</example>

<para>
What happens if a player targets an opponent's eye or another body part and
miss by one on his attack roll? Since we don't want to get into overly
complicated and cumbersome mechanics, we leave this to the interpretation of
the GM. It could either be treated as a complete miss, a hit to a nearby bone
that only does normal Impact or a full hit to the head.
Situational modifiers that may influence this decision include the movement
speed of the opponent, the fact that he may be wearing a helmet, etc. 
</para>

<table frame="all"><title>Size</title>
<tgroup cols="4" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colnum="4" align="left" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Size Factor</entry><entry>SR</entry><entry>Size</entry><entry>Creature, body part or object</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>0.0155</entry><entry>-15</entry><entry>3cm</entry><entry>Human eye</entry></row>
<row><entry>0.0205</entry><entry>-14</entry><entry>4cm</entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>0.0270</entry><entry>-13</entry><entry>5cm</entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>0.0357</entry><entry>-12</entry><entry>6cm</entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>0.0471</entry><entry>-11</entry><entry>8cm</entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>0.0623</entry><entry>-10</entry><entry>11cm</entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>0.0822</entry><entry>-9</entry><entry>15cm</entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>0.108</entry><entry>-8</entry><entry>19cm</entry><entry>Human hand, Human throat</entry></row>
<row><entry>0.143</entry><entry>-7</entry><entry>26cm</entry><entry>Dagger</entry></row>
<row><entry>0.189</entry><entry>-6</entry><entry>34cm</entry><entry>Human head</entry></row>
<row><entry>0.250</entry><entry>-5</entry><entry>45cm</entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>0.329</entry><entry>-4</entry><entry>59cm</entry><entry>Human arm</entry></row>
<row><entry>0.435</entry><entry>-3</entry><entry>78cm</entry><entry>Human leg</entry></row>
<row><entry>0.574</entry><entry>-2</entry><entry>1.0m</entry><entry>Human chest</entry></row>
<row><entry>0.758</entry><entry>-1</entry><entry>1.4m </entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>1.0</entry><entry>0</entry><entry>1.8m</entry><entry>Human, Elf</entry></row>
<row><entry>1.32</entry><entry>1</entry><entry>2.4m </entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>1.74</entry><entry>2</entry><entry>3.1m </entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>2.30</entry><entry>3</entry><entry>4.1m </entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>3.04</entry><entry>4</entry><entry>5.5m </entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>4.01</entry><entry>5</entry><entry>7.2m </entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>5.29</entry><entry>6</entry><entry>9.5m </entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>6.98</entry><entry>7</entry><entry>13m </entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>9.22</entry><entry>8</entry><entry>17m </entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>12.2</entry><entry>9</entry><entry>22m </entry><entry></entry></row>
<row><entry>16.1</entry><entry>10</entry><entry>29m </entry><entry></entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<formalpara><title>Size Factor</title>
<para>
A number showing a creature's size relative to humans.
<literal>
Size Factor = 1.32^SR
</literal>
</para>
</formalpara>
             
<formalpara><title>SR</title>
<para>
Size Rating, to be used in called shots.
<literal>
SR = log1.32(Size Factor)
</literal>
</para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Size</title>
<para>
The average size of a creature or object with a certain SR. Mainly based on
height, but also factors is width.
</para>
</formalpara>
                 
<formalpara><title>Creature, body part or object</title>
<para>
An example creature, body part or object of a given size rating.
</para>
</formalpara>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Targeting with Missile Weapons</title>
<para>
Missile Weapon Styles are handled as standard Skills, with a TD that is
mainly dependent on the distance between your character and its target. For
simplicity, the base TD does not depend on the weapon used and is given in the
following table:
</para>

<table frame="all"><title>Targeting with Missile Weapons</title>
<tgroup cols="3" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<colspec colnum="3" align="center" colwidth="1*" />
<thead>
<row><entry>Distance</entry><entry>Range</entry><entry>Base TD</entry></row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Near</entry><entry>0 to 10 meters</entry><entry>0</entry></row>
<row><entry>Moderate</entry><entry>11 to 50 meters</entry><entry>5</entry></row>
<row><entry>Far</entry><entry>51 to 100 meters</entry><entry>10</entry></row>
<row><entry>Extreme</entry><entry>&gt; 100 meters</entry><entry>15</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<para>
The targeting equation is:
</para>

<para>
<literal>
d10-d10* + Missile Weapon Skill &gt;= TD
</literal>
</para>

<para>
Since all missile weapons are not equal in effectiveness, an effective range
is associated with each one. When the target is beyond a weapon's effective
range, additional penalties are applied to the task difficulty. The TD
increases by 1 for each 10% over the weapons effective range (round up).
As usual, the GM can either apply this rule as a strict rule, as a
simple guideline or even completely dismiss it. Sometimes, it is simpler to
just consider all situational modifiers and make a quick decision on the TD.
</para>

<para>
Missile weapons also have a maximum range beyond which they cannot send a
missile. This maximum range is normally listed in the weapons description.
</para>

<para>
Damage and called shots are handled in the same manner as for melee attacks.
</para>

<example><title>Targeting</title>
<screen>
In the following examples, we use one weapon of each group: a dagger,
(effect. range: 15m; max. range: 40m), a short bow (effect. range: 90m; max.
range: 225m) and a heavy arbalest (effect. range: 60m, max range: 330m).

Situation 1: Target is 8 meters away.
  TD is 0 with all three weapons, since the target is near and within their 
  effective range.

Situation 2: Target is 20 meters away.
  TD is 9 with the dagger since the target is in medium range (TD 5) and is
  5 meters over the dagger's effective range. (20 - 15) / 1.5 ~= 3.3 = 4.
  TD is 5 with both the short bow and arbalest, since the target is within
  their effective range.

Situation 3: Target is 100 meters away.
  Such a dagger throw is "impossible" since the target is beyond the dagger's
  maximum range.
  TD is 11 with the short bow since the target is far (TD 10) and is
  10 meters over the bow's effective range. (100 - 90) / 9 ~= 1.1 = 2.
  TD is 17 with the heavy arbalest since the target is far (TD 10) and is
  40 meters over the bow's effective range. (100 - 60) / 6 ~= 6.7 = 7.

Situation 4: Target is 500 meters away.
  Don't even think about it...
</screen>
</example>

<para>
Targeting TD Formula:
</para>

<para>
<literal>
TD = (Range - Effective Range) / 10% of Effective Range
</literal>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Optional:
In some situations, it makes sense to take into account the size of the
target. In these cases, the TD can be modified by substracting from it the
SR of the target.
</emphasis>
</para>

<example><title><emphasis>Size Rating Adjustments</emphasis></title>
<screen>
<emphasis>
Hitting a giant (SR: 4) standing 20 meters away with with a short bow has a
TD of 1, while hitting a weejon (SR: -3) at the same distance has a TD of 8.
</emphasis>
</screen>
</example>

<para>
<emphasis>
As a reference, humans have a SR = 0. The game master is free to apply this rule
whenever he wishes.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
<literal>
Size Rating Adjustement: Adjusted TD = Standard TD - SR
</literal>
</emphasis>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Damage and Injury</title>
<para>
When a successful hit has been scored, Damage is computed by substracting
the defender's Resistance from the attacker's Impact.
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Damage = Impact - Resistance
</literal>
</para>

<para>
The attacker's Impact is the sum of his Strength and his weapon's Impact:
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Impact = Weapon Impact + STR
</literal>
</para>

<para>
The Resistance of the defender is the sum of his Natural Resistance and
his armor's Resistance:
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Resistance = Natural Resistance + Armor Resistance
</literal>
</para>

<para>
Armor Resistance is always a positive value that depends on the type of
armor being worn. Natural Resistance is a value representing the natural
body covering of a species (see the species description). Natural Resistance
can be negative. Because of this, Resistance can be negative as well.
</para>

<para>
If Damage is lower than 0, then it is considered to be 0. A Damage of 0 or
less is considered to be just a scratch. If Damage is greater than 0, then
it should be added to the Injury heap.
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Injury = Injury + Damage
</literal>
</para>

<example><title>Impact and Injury</title>
<screen>
Game situation:
  (first round)
  To determine the Impact done by Neila's hit on the skeleton, Bob rolls
  11 on 2d6+4 (the war hammer Impact) and adds Neila's STR for a total of
  14. The GM substract the Natural Resistance (5) of the Guardian from
  Neila's Impact and adds 9 to the Guardian's Injury Heap (previously at 0).

  (sixth round) (Note that Damage calculations are normally done just
  after determining if an attack was successful. All Damage calculations
  are presented here in the same section for explanation purposes)
  -&gt; Neila hits the first skeleton for 11+3=14 points of Impact. This
     increases the skeleton's Injury by 9 to a total of 36.
  -&gt; The second skeleton hits Neila for 8+2=10 for a Damage of 4 after
     the attack has passed through the armor (Resistance=6). This
     brings her Injury heap to 26.
  -&gt; Jalik hits the third skeleton for 6 points of Impact. Only 1 point
     passes the skeleton's Natural Resistance, bringing its Injury
     Heap to 24.
  -&gt; The third skeleton does 13 points of Impact to Jalik. His armor only
     absorbs 3 points, adding 10 points of Damage to Injury, for a total
     of 18.
</screen>
</example>

<sect4><title><emphasis>Bonus Impact (Optional)</emphasis></title>
<para>
<emphasis>
<literal>
Bonus Impact = [SA [+ SA mods] - (TD [+ TD mods] + SD [+ SD mods])] / 2
             = (Total SA - Total SD) / 2
</literal>
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
This is the same formula used for standard targeting, only instead of just
comparing the sides we find how mush greater the left hand side is.
If the Bonus Impact is less than 0, the attack misses.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Note that for every 2 points of success above the TD, the Bonus Impact is
increased by 1.
</emphasis>
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
<literal>
Total Impact = Bonus Impact + Weapon Impact
</literal>
</emphasis>
</para>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Multiple Actions in Combat</title>
<para>
The Multiple Actions mechanism is used frequently in combat. When a
character wants to defend against multiple opponents, he has to buy Multiple
Actions for a penalty of 5 on all his Skills. Each additional Combat Style
action gives both one attack and one defense.
</para>

<example><title>Multiple Actions in Combat</title>
<screen>
If a character attacks and defends against two opponents, his two attacks and
two defenses are done with a -5 penalty. Similarly a character attacking one
opponent and dodging two others would have a -5 on his rolls in both his Combat
Style and Dodge Skill.
</screen>
</example>

<para>
Actions that are not related to combat also impose a -5 penalty on all Skill
checks when they are performed while the character fights. If a character
wants to catch an object while fighting, he would face a -5 penalty on both
his catching roll and his attack and defense.
</para>

<para>
Note that the defense Skill of the character can never be lowered below 0 by
any penalty, since a defense of 0 is that of a moving target within range.
It is considered that your character cannot do worse if he tries to defend
than if he does not try to.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2><title>Survival checks</title>
<para>
At the end of the combat round, after all actions have been resolved, every 
combatant that has been injured during the round (i.e. that has seen his 
Injury Heap increase) must make Unconciousness and Death checks.
</para>

<para>
An Unconsciousness check is made by rolling d10-d10* and adding 25 plus the
character's Willpower and Body. If the total is greater than or equal to
Injury, then the check is successful and the character stays conscious.
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Unconsciousness: d10-d10* + 25 + BOD + WIL &gt;= Injury
</literal>
</para>

<para>
It is not necessary to make an Unconsciousness check if 25 + Body + Wilpower is
over Injury by 10 points or more.
</para>

<para>
A Death check is similarly made by rolling d10-d10* and adding 40 and the
character's Body. If the total is greater than or equal to the Injury, then
the check is successful and the character stays alive.
</para>

<para>
<literal>
Death: d10-d10* + 40 + BOD &gt;= Injury
</literal>
</para>

<para>
It is not necessary to make a Death check if 40 + Bodyis greater than Injury
by 10 points or more.
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>
Optional:
If the Graded Outcomes rules are used, a partial outcome indicates that the
character is not Unconscious but suffers from such pain that he is not able to
do anything beside moaning and screaming. He remains generally aware of what is
happening around him.
</emphasis>
</para>

<example><title>Survival Checks</title>
<screen>
Game situation:
  (first round) The Injury heap of the first Skeleton Guardian is now equal 
  to 9. Since this is much lower than 40 plus the Body of the skeleton,
  there is no need for a Death check (the skeleton does not check for
  Unconsciousness, see description).

  (sixth round)
  -&gt; Bob's roll for Neila: -3 + 25 + 2 (WIL) + 2 (BOD) = 26 (Injury)
     Neila remains conscious enough to continue the fight. 
  -&gt; Roger's roll for Jalik: -2 + 25 + 0 (WIL) + 1 (BOD) &gt; 18 (Injury)
     Jalik remains conscious.
  -&gt; GM's roll for the 1st skeleton:
     -6 + 40 + 0 (BOD) &lt; 36 (Injury)
     The skeleton crumbles into a heap of broken bones.
  -&gt; The Injury of the third skeleton (24) is much lower than his 
     BOD (0) + 40, so there is no need for a death check.
</screen>
</example>
</sect2>
</sect1>
